<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Surinam justice in the case of several persons proscribed by certain usurpers of power in that colony : being a publication of that perfect relation of the beginning, continuance, and end of the late disturbances in the colony of Surinam, set forth under that title, by William Byam Esq. (sometime rightfull) governour of that colony : and the vindication of those gentlemen, sufferers by his injustice, form the calummies wherewith he asperseth them in that relation / couched in the answer thereunto by Robert Sanford ...</title>
            <author>Sanford, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37524</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16966628</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16966628</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30795)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1610:43)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Surinam justice in the case of several persons proscribed by certain usurpers of power in that colony : being a publication of that perfect relation of the beginning, continuance, and end of the late disturbances in the colony of Surinam, set forth under that title, by William Byam Esq. (sometime rightfull) governour of that colony : and the vindication of those gentlemen, sufferers by his injustice, form the calummies wherewith he asperseth them in that relation / couched in the answer thereunto by Robert Sanford ...</title>
                  <author>Sanford, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the authour ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Each section of 'Byams declaration' and each deposition sworn before him is followed by Sanford's 'answer.' "--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Byam, William, 1623-1670.</term>
               <term>Suriname --  Politics and government --  To 1814.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Colonies --  Administration.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Surinam Juſtice. IN THE CASE Of ſeveral perſons proſcribed by certain Uſurpers of Power in that COLONY.</p>
            <p>BEING A Publication of that perfect Relation of the Beginning, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, and End of the late Diſturbances in the <hi>Colony</hi> of SURINAM, ſet forth under that Title, by <hi>William Byam</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> (ſometime Rightfull) Governour of that <hi>Colony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND <hi>The Vindication of thoſe Gentlemen, ſufferers by his inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, from the Calumnies wherewith he aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them in that Relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Couched in the Anſwer thereunto By ROBERT SANFORD.</p>
            <q>Neither leaſt in Innocence nor in Sufferings.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Nec mori vereor, nec vivere, virtute ſalva<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Laeſa, &amp; mori &amp; vivere.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Authour, and are to be ſold at the <hi>Braſen Serpent</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>George Stradling,</hi> S.T.P. Rev. in Chriſto Pat. <hi>Guil.</hi> Epiſc. Lond. a Sac. Domest.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aed. ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud. <date>
                     <hi>14. Octob. 1662.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lords Commiſſioners appointed by his Sacred Majeſty to conſult the Affairs of his Foreign Plantations.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eaſon could not direct me to a better way to let your Lordſhips underſtand the <hi>whole</hi> of my caſe, then by preſenting you with the full charge my adverſaries have publiſhed againſt me, with ſuch anſwer to it as <hi>truth</hi> and my own <hi>innocence</hi> prompted me to make. Here your Honours will finde all the criminations which their <hi>inventions</hi> could ſuperadd to the <hi>proofs</hi> brought againſt us, and my refutation of them, which are <hi>both</hi> ſubjected to your Lordſhips judgement.</p>
            <p>That this Narrative which I have expoſed to publick view is <hi>Byam</hi>'s <hi>own;</hi> I can onely bring theſe Arguments for: when I came to <hi>Barbadoes</hi> (which was long after the departure of my fellow-Proſcripts from <hi>Suri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam</hi>) <hi>Byam,</hi> not doubting their arrival, gave onely ſhort accounts to his friends <hi>there</hi> of thoſe rancounters amongst us, referring them to <hi>this Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> ſent formerly: But <hi>they,</hi> miſcarried by their leaky veſſel, came not to that <hi>Iſland</hi> till I was departed thence, and then <hi>this Declaration</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came first publick <hi>there.</hi> Among divers copies, one of them was ſent to my Vncle (well intereſſed in <hi>Surinam</hi>) with a letter from <hi>Byam</hi> aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my particular fact: <hi>He</hi> ſent <hi>both</hi> to me, and I, as faithfully as I could tranſcribe them, have ſent <hi>both</hi> into the world. I can, I believe, finde ſome here who having ſeen and read them before they came to my hands, dare ſo far rely on their memories as to aver theſe to be the very ſame.</p>
            <p>Here now, my Lords, you have both the parties pleading before your Honours: in the <hi>conteſt,</hi> the diſadvantage of the weapons is obſervable; <hi>They,</hi> having afflicted us with the greatest injuries, have nothing to doe but to be dirt us with any imputation which may render us criminal enough for the puniſhments we have ſuffered: <hi>We</hi> are forced to bring <hi>Proofs</hi> of our Innocence againſt <hi>their no-proofs</hi> of our guilt, or elſe muct fall under
<pb facs="tcp:105536:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and aſperſions: as though it were argument enough of our cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>at we have ſo highly ſuffered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly it is a hard task <hi>to prove negatives,</hi> but ſurely a much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er caſe <hi>that ſuffering Innocence</hi> muſt be put to it, while he that hath vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated her is credited on his bare aſſertion: yet <hi>this is our task and our caſe,</hi> and how I have performed it, and acquitted my ſelf and friends of their defamations your Lordſhips alone can judge.</p>
            <p>This I ſhall chiefly urge, our enemies do here confeſſe that they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoiled us of reputation and liberty by an infamous impriſonment, of goods, by heavy fines, of houſes, lands, and of countrey by baniſhment, and all this by an uſurpt power, and an arbitrary tyrannical way of proceedings, by the force of an army, deſtroying the <hi>Birth-right</hi> of the ſubject. If they muſt have credit given to all their criminations againſt us, I hope they will not he permitted to traverſe what they have confeſſed of themſelves: If then, to ſubvert the ſacred fundamental Sanctions of our Nation, to tread under foot the laws eſtabliſhed for the preſervation of perſons and proprieties, to uſurp Dominion, that branch of <hi>Regality,</hi> to congregate an armed force without warrant, and therewith to invade the <hi>Rights</hi> of their fellow-ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, be crimes of a <hi>mid-night-hew,</hi> I hope they may be as well underſtood when they charge themſelves with all this, as when they accuſe us of what is leſſe evident. Since alſo the Honour, Libertie, and Eſtates of the ſubjests are in the protection of the King and his laws, why ſhould not theſe perſons be accountable <hi>to them,</hi> how rightly they have deprived us of all theſe?</p>
            <p>But they think to juſtifie their proceedings againſt us by the <hi>names</hi> of a <hi>General Aſſembly and the united Authority of the Countrey,</hi> when it is known that the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> though <hi>duly Authorized,</hi> neither <hi>there</hi> nor in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> was ever a Court of Judicature, eſpecially in criminal caſes, <hi>ſuch</hi> being always tried by the Governour, aſsiſted by all the Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at the General Seſsions of the Peace, where the fact is preſented by a Grand Inquest, and after found <hi>done or not done</hi> by a Jury of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood. And <hi>this</hi> is according to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and to <hi>this way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi> the Authority of <hi>Surinam</hi> were bound by their own <hi>Act,</hi> beſides the <hi>General fundamental Conſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſhould we grant that it were customary in thoſe Colonies to try of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences by the <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> contrary to the great <hi>Charter,</hi> it would not excuſe a company of men who ſeiz to themſelves the <hi>Power and Name of a General Aſſembly,</hi> and vote all thoſe that deny their Authority, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what crimes they pleaſe, ſparing or puniſhing them according to the <hi>Rule of their wills.</hi> What they call ſedition in us, they confeſſe to be onely a diſputing their power, and an <hi>Act of Parliament cannot authorize any to be Judges in their own cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:3"/>
            <p>My Lords, as we cannot looſe our <hi>Allegiance</hi> by changing or ſoil or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo neither can we looſe the <hi>Royal Protection.</hi> And that ſubject that hazards life, and fortunes to enlarge his <hi>Majeſties Dominions, the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of his crown, and traffick of the Nation,</hi> deſerves not to be <hi>diſenfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould not importune your Lordſhips with a repeated clamour of my caſe, did I groan under a ſupportable ſufferance: but wholly to looſe an eſtate purchaſed by a large expence of money, time and travel: to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from a plentiful way of being to the nearest confines of Beggery; from the dignity of ſtore, to the contempts of want; to be deprived of <hi>that fruition, which</hi> when it was in hope onely did ſweeten the toil of its ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quist; and what is the <hi>ſum of all,</hi> to ſee a wife and children, dear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, panting under <hi>this whole burthen;</hi> is ſo ſuperlative a puniſhment, that I cannot believe <hi>all they would make me guilty of</hi> can deſerve it: <hi>Death,</hi> though murther, had been a <hi>mercy to this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>this,</hi> my Lords, without <hi>Hyperbole or</hi> aggravation, is truly my condition: whatever I brought into that Colony, and whatever improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>that</hi> my induſtry had made (which was ſufficiently conſiderable) is ſo wholly gone, that not the leaſt Remains thereof are left; lands I have <hi>there,</hi> but ſuch as lie waſte, and, without money to reſtock them, must for ever lye ſo; and though my enemies malice go not ſo far as to forfeit them, their heavy impoſitions will devour them.</p>
            <p>They have ſo weakened me (ſuch was their cruel policy) that I can ſcarce call for Juſtice: by the Grandeur of their oppreſſion they have made the moſt probable purchaſe of their own impunity; and their example will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thoſe that ſhall hear after meditate wrong, <hi>to doe it fully;</hi> unleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred by the impartial ſcrutiny, your Lordſhips ſhall make into theſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and your <hi>laying</hi> or <hi>leaving the puniſhment where you finde the guilt:</hi> which unfeignedly is the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humble Servant, R. SANFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>F in <hi>this Narrative</hi> my <hi>phraſe</hi> or <hi>ſtile</hi> be beneath the <hi>elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and purer Dialect</hi> of our <hi>Eaſtern Engliſh,</hi> and that in any particular I expreſs my ſelf in an <hi>Idiom different</hi> from what <hi>uſe</hi> hath made <hi>common</hi> in theſe Parts, I deſire the <hi>Reader</hi> to be <hi>favourable</hi> in his <hi>cenſure:</hi> For (beſides that in this I rather ſtudied <hi>truth</hi> then <hi>words</hi>) it is <hi>more than an excuſe</hi> to ſay, I was tranſplanted in my very child-hood into the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> where I ſpent my <hi>whole puerility and adoleſcence, all the time proper for Erudition,</hi> and the <hi>poliſhings</hi> of my <hi>now-entered viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Near twenty years</hi> have I been abſent from my <hi>native Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> the greater and better part of <hi>which I loſt</hi> in places <hi>unrefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> from their <hi>aboriginal Barbariſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. SANFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105536:4"/>
            <head>Surinam Juſtice.</head>
            <div n="1" type="declaration">
               <head>Byams Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 1 <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Governour of</hi> Surinam <hi>hath been for theſe three years paſt, annually Elected by Delegates choſen by the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders thereof: A Power which</hi> Neceſſity <hi>enforced them to aſſume during the Diſtractions of our Nation, but alwaies with ſubmiſſion to the</hi> Supream Authority <hi>of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon his Majeſties happy Reſtauration,</hi> advice <hi>being brought of his</hi> Royal Proclamation <hi>for the Continuance of all</hi> Governours, <hi>Magiſtrates and other Officers till further Order, it was in Obedience to the</hi> ſame <hi>una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly Concluded and Ordered at a</hi> General Aſſembly <hi>as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Governour and General Aſſembly.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Since by his Majeſties late Proclamation all Governours</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Of Colonys are Required to Continue and Execute their ſeveral Offices in His Majeſties Name till further Order; and ſince it is daily expected that Particular Orders will ſuddenly arrive from his Majeſty to this Colony for the Government thereof, ſo that the</hi> Meeting <hi>of the Inhabitants for the</hi> Electing of Repreſentatives <hi>will be but a needleſſe and unneceſſary</hi> Charge and Trouble <hi>to the Inhabitants. It is therefore Ordered that all Perſons reſt quiet and contented in Obedience to the Authority aforeſaid, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all neceſſary Duties and Injunctions from them Proceeding, till they are Concluded by ſuch alterations as his Sacred Majeſty ſhall think conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to appoint amongst us.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Dated <date>the eight day of <hi>May</hi> 1661.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 1. Thoſe <hi>Delegates</hi> were Choſen by the People to Erect the <hi>whole frame of Government,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> accordingly did (as formerly, ſo) in the Beginning of this laſt year appoint the <hi>whole General Aſſembly;</hi> and <hi>limited</hi> the time of <hi>their Rule</hi> preciſely to an Anniverſary day, on which the Election of the <hi>whole Authority</hi> was to be <hi>by the People</hi> repeated: and <hi>this Power</hi> was not onely to ſubmit to the <hi>Supream Authority,</hi> but to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern Conformly to the <hi>Lawes</hi> of England. Nor was <hi>that Neceſſity which</hi> during the Diſtractions of our Nation Enforced them to <hi>this courſe,</hi> viz. <hi>[No Commands from the Soveraign for a Government]</hi> at all taken away by His Majeſties happy Reſtauration; <hi>the Proclamation</hi> they ſpeak of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a meer <hi>Chimaera</hi> of <hi>Byam</hi>'s own Brain, invented to ſerve <hi>his Ambition</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105536:5"/>of a <hi>Perpetual Dominion, ſo often</hi> and by <hi>ſo many Arts</hi> formerly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured.</p>
               <p>Take away then <hi>ſo much</hi> of the Preamble of <hi>This Order</hi> as concern's <hi>that Proclamation,</hi> and we find onely thoſe <hi>ſtale Inducements</hi> (often here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore uſed, and as often hiſt't out) viz. [<hi>a ſudden change,</hi> and therefore <hi>unneceſſary trouble to continue the former Rule for Elections.</hi>] But <hi>this Conſideration</hi> neither <hi>concerns,</hi> nor is of weight to <hi>Authorize,</hi> a <hi>Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Power</hi> to alter thoſe Conſtitutions which by their <hi>Superiour Power</hi> were Eſtabliſhed: for a <hi>leſs Potency</hi> then <hi>that</hi> which <hi>creates</hi> cannot <hi>anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilate.</hi> Nor can it Logically be ſaid that the <hi>Delegates</hi> by inveſting this General Aſſembly with a Legiſlative and Magiſtratical Power for a <hi>year</hi> did by thoſe words paſſe <hi>ſuch Power</hi> to them <hi>for ever;</hi> ſo that though we ſhould grant that <hi>within their year</hi> they could make <hi>ſuch an Order,</hi> it would not follow that <hi>after their year expired</hi> they could <hi>put it in Execution by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Obedience to it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>The Date of this Order was above a Moneth before my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion expired; Here</hi> Democracy <hi>fell, by the Loyal Conceſſions of our Government to the Royal Power of</hi> Monarchy: <hi>which was communicated by the Gentlemen of the General Aſſembly to the Inhabitants of their</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Diviſions <hi>as occaſion preſented; and</hi> all <hi>for about four Moneths Reſigned their Submiſſion unto it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 2 By <hi>Democracy</hi> here, we muſt underſtand <hi>the Conſtitutions of the Peoples Delegates;</hi> and by <hi>the Governments conceſsions to Monarchy,</hi> the <hi>altering that conſtitution upon the ſuſpition of a Royal Proclamation</hi> to that purpoſe iſſued forth: for if they mean the General Submiſſion of the Colony to the King as our ſupream Lord, why ſhould not this <hi>Democracy</hi> have fallen as well in <hi>Olivers and Richards</hi> time (as it was attempted with the <hi>like Pretexts</hi>) <hi>whoſe power Byam</hi> recognized with equal zeal as he did <hi>His Majeſties?</hi> No argument can evince but that, <hi>That forme of Government</hi> appointed by the Delegates might very well <hi>ſtill</hi> have Conſiſted with our ſubjection to the Soveraign Power of England.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>About the latter end of October following I committed</hi> Daniel Jones <hi>a Carpenter to the Marſhal, for contemning, ſleighting, abuſing the Authority of the Colony; as alſo for his obſtinate refuſing to pay a fine impoſed on him by the</hi> General Aſſembly <hi>for his former inſufferable Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: with command that he ſhould be kept in</hi> Irons <hi>till further Order, there being then no Priſon of ſecurity in the Colony.</hi> Mr. Michael Maſhart
<pb facs="tcp:105536:5"/>
                  <hi>interpoſed for his Releaſe on Baile, which I refuſing, cauſed</hi> Mr. Maſhart <hi>that night being</hi> (<hi>the</hi> 27<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> October) <hi>in the height of his Cups, not onely</hi> to deny, <hi>but to</hi> ſtand in defiance <hi>of the Authority of the Colony.</hi> Jones <hi>Eſcaping from the negligent Marſhall flyes to</hi> Maſhart; <hi>they both quit their houſes and betake themſelves to the woods and to their armes: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ſent</hi> Sergeant Major George Uſher <hi>to</hi> Maſhart <hi>to require his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance before me;</hi> Maſhart <hi>told him</hi> he would own no Governour nor any Authority in the Colony.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 3. Though <hi>generalls</hi> prove nothing, and as little credit be to be given to <hi>his criminations</hi> who is himſelf guilty of unjuſt proſecutions, yet I ſhall not decline to Evince that <hi>Joues could not</hi> (at the time mentioned) <hi>ſlight, contemne, or abuſe Authority.</hi> For admit we had not a greater truth for the Aſſertion, yet according to that Rule of my Lord <hi>Cookes [De non apparentibus &amp; non exiſtentibus eademest ratio]</hi> we may rationally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, from its never being ſeen or publiſhed amongſt us, that <hi>there never was any ſuch Proclamation from the King as they ground their Authority up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> &amp; <hi>that foundation</hi> being removed they have <hi>none</hi> for their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For the power which they derived from the <hi>Delegates</hi> was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by <hi>their expreſſe limitation</hi> on the ſecond wedneſday in June; ſo that the Dominion which they were poſſeſſed of in <hi>October following</hi> was <hi>taken by themſelves,</hi> and is conſequently an <hi>Uſurpation;</hi> and whether <hi>that</hi> can be ſufficiently ſlighted, contemned or abuſed, let <hi>them</hi> reſolve who yet feel the calamities of our late times in England.</p>
               <p>I never thought <hi>flying from Perſecution</hi> had been ranged with <hi>reſiſtance to Power;</hi> atd wonder as much how <hi>Uſher</hi> could find <hi>Maſharts Receſses,</hi> and return unoffended from his <hi>Armes:</hi> a little proofe would have done well; ſome <hi>Illuſtration</hi> at leaſt to bring the <hi>tale together.</hi> It ſhould ſeem if they did betake themſelves to armes it was <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> ſo natural as that the Law dares not puniſh it.</p>
               <p>Nor was it <hi>Jones</hi>'s inſufferable Inſolence, but <hi>Byams</hi> and <hi>Martens</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatred, that impoſed that <hi>former fine:</hi> as Illegally and Arbitralily as his latter fine and Baniſhment was decreed: they might have remembred the Precedents I cited againſt that <hi>Judgement,</hi> which they could <hi>then</hi> no otherwiſe anſwer than by <hi>straffords</hi> caſe <hi>attainted by Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. <hi>But before I proceed it will be requiſite to adviſe that on the</hi> 13<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> February 1660. <hi>there was an Act made by the General Aſſembly for a Levy upon land of halfe a pound of Sugar per Acre, to be paid at two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral payments: this Aſſeſsment was to diſcharge publick debts, build a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105536:6"/>State-houſe and a Priſon (which was Gall to the Debauehers of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) and alſo for a Stock in the Treaſury:</hi> Maſhart <hi>and</hi> Jones, <hi>meeting with the Inhabitants of the</hi> Diviſion <hi>where they lived, were the firſt that claſhed and ſtormed against it; In ſo much that at that time nothing was done as required: whereupon about a week after I ſummoned all the Inhabitants again, but</hi> Maſhart <hi>and</hi> Jones <hi>appeared not: I then Declared unto them upon what</hi> Baſis <hi>the</hi> Government <hi>ſtood, and the neceſſity of this Levy; which very much</hi> ſatisfied <hi>the people: and that</hi> Maſhart <hi>may be inexcuſeable,</hi> Capt. Thomas Griffith, <hi>one of the</hi> Repreſentatives <hi>of</hi> that Diviſion, <hi>did, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the middle of</hi> July <hi>last, informe the ſaid</hi> Maſhart <hi>at his houſe of the Order of the</hi> General Aſſembly, <hi>in Obedience to His</hi> Majeſties Proclamation <hi>concerning our preſent Government: the</hi> ſame <hi>I adviſed Maſhart the</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember <hi>following, with which he then told me he was ſatisfied,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 4. This Section ſhould precede the former as the <hi>cauſe</hi> doth the <hi>effect;</hi> for the demanding of <hi>this Levy</hi> when the <hi>Aſſeſsors</hi> power was legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expired, was it indeed which raiſed the <hi>Diſpute</hi> againſt the pretended Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. The people <hi>before</hi> onely <hi>muttered</hi> at the loſſe of <hi>their Priviledges,</hi> but when they began to ſee an approaching loſſe of <hi>what</hi> with ſo much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty they laboured for, they grew <hi>louder</hi> in their <hi>clamours:</hi> and thinking themſelves well fortified with arguments, denyed the power which demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>this</hi> of them: hoping to lighten their burthen by a <hi>new Election, which hopes</hi> was <hi>Byams</hi> and his Partiſans <hi>deſpair.</hi> Nor muſt we think every <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> a <hi>Satisfiedneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>On the</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> October <hi>at the meeting of the Inhabitants of the</hi> Diviſion <hi>of</hi> Toorarica, Mr. William Sanford <hi>(one of the Confederacy) did alſo very Inſolently ſpit in the face of Authority, ſtirring up the people to</hi> ſedition; <hi>and was uncontrolled by his brother,</hi> Lieutenant Coll. Robert Sanford, <hi>then preſent; a</hi> Magiſtrate <hi>and one of my</hi> Councel; <hi>who afterwards appeared to</hi> head <hi>the</hi> Faction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 5. That <hi>Mr. William Sanford</hi> at the meeting of the Inhabitants of <hi>Toorárica</hi> about <hi>this Levy</hi> did deny payment thereof till he was ſatisfied by what power it was demanded, openly denying the Governours Power, I ſhall readily acknowledge; but that he did <hi>thereby</hi> inſolently ſpit in the face of Authority I muſt deny, for the reaſons afore-alledged. That he was uncontrolled by me I underſtand not; for <hi>the ſame</hi> that <hi>Byam</hi> ſaith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did upon the like occaſion in <hi>Maſharts Diviſion,</hi> I did <hi>here,</hi> and <hi>thereby</hi> ſilenced my brother. Perhaps he counts him <hi>uncontrolled,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105536:6"/>
                  <hi>uncommanded</hi> into <hi>Irons</hi> as <hi>Jones</hi> was: (which exaſperated <hi>Maſhart,</hi> my brother, and divers others.) But though I was one of <hi>Byams Councel,</hi> I was not of his <hi>Cloſet;</hi> and my <hi>Magiſtrates oath</hi> (which he never took) deterred me from <hi>ſuch lawleſs ſeverities.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>Theſe two pretended Grievances which they ſeemed to boggle at, the</hi> Levy <hi>and the</hi> Government (<hi>in the latter of</hi> which <hi>they objected</hi> the peoples liberties were infringed) <hi>were but Cloaks for a farther deſigne. For about ſix or eight (I mention the moſt) male-contents; of bad fortunes, worſe lives, and no endeavours, envying the proſperity of the induſtrious and obſerving their own declining condition, occaſionod through continued ſloth and drunkenneſs, were reſolved, if poſſible, to unhinge the frame of Authority, bring all things into a confuſed diſorder, and out of the troubles (which their ſottiſh diſtemper had fancied) patch up their decaying fortunes. The truth of</hi> this <hi>and what elſe I aſſert, will moſt evidently appear out of the annexed Depoſitions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 6. When the world reads there were but ſix or eight ſo very bad as are here deſcribed, and after hears that <hi>eight onely</hi> were baniſhed, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but in charity conclude <hi>thoſe eight</hi> to be the very worſt; and ſo amongſt our other ſufferings we muſt wander the world with all <hi>this filth</hi> upon us. But till a contrary proofe appear, <hi>this aſſertion</hi> may be full as current, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three fourths of theſe Proſcripts brought better fortunes into that Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by many degrees, than <hi>Byam</hi> or the more numerous of <hi>his aſſeſſors:</hi> (their <hi>fines</hi> are ſome evidence of this.) Nor were they <hi>leſs induſtrious</hi> in improving <hi>thoſe fortunes:</hi> many of them alſo were ſeldome exempted from the moſt eminent employments. And if drunkenneſſe be a crime meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in our enemies thoughts, of ſo ſharp and ſevere a puniſhment as we have undergone, I wonder <hi>they</hi> were not <hi>themſelves</hi> deterred (or aſhamed at the leaſt) ſo publickly to become <hi>examples</hi> of <hi>exceſs</hi> in <hi>that kinde, that</hi> very night in <hi>which</hi> they had determined concerning us. But I will excuſe them as tranſported with Joy, and confeſſe that <hi>Recriminations</hi> purge not the guilty. And heartily I do wiſh that <hi>this fault</hi> could be leſſe objected to any of us, or to our Nation: <hi>this</hi> I ſhall onely averre, very few of <hi>us Exiles,</hi> did ever any injury, either to publick or private Intereſts, by <hi>Ebriety:</hi> a <hi>Negation</hi> to a <hi>bare Affirmative</hi> is enough; and the <hi>likelihood</hi> of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plots objected in <hi>this Paragraph</hi> we will examine in our anſwer to the <hi>next,</hi> and to the <hi>Depoſitions</hi> annexed to <hi>which</hi> they referre us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. <hi>During part of theſe rebellions diſſentions</hi> Lieutenant Coll. San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105536:7"/>
                  <hi>was commanded abroad with a party to ſatisfy the timerous</hi> Indians, <hi>who ſuſpected we had a deſigne to cut them off: with him were many of our boſome enemies, who all the voyage endeavoured to diſcompoſe the mindes of the Souldiers, pretending they would get what number and ſettle</hi> S. Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents: <hi>I waited his return to ſummon the General Aſſembly, whereof</hi> he and Captain Strange <hi>(at that time with him) were Members: and though I was adviſed by ſeveral that</hi> he <hi>was the grand Promoter of theſe diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances yet I was ſtill incredulous.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 7. The Diſputes made to their preſent Authority being ſo reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and juſt, <hi>Byam</hi> to make it a Crime is forced to accuſe it of <hi>Pregnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> a <hi>guilt big</hi> with <hi>Monſter,</hi> the <hi>Prodromus</hi> to the Colonyes deſtruction; as though the new Electing <hi>their Repreſentatives, now</hi> more than <hi>ever,</hi> muſt be the onely narrow way for <hi>its ruine</hi> to enter at. Yet herein he is ſo unlucky as to aſſert what every child almoſt in that Colony can contradict: for he layes the Inducements to this plot to be diſcontent, bad fortunes, worſe lives, and no-endeavours, and (the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all theſe) ſloth and drunkenneſſe; and at the ſame inſtant makes Mr. <hi>Michael Maſhart,</hi> Mr. <hi>Daniel Jones</hi> and my <hi>Brother,</hi> the firſt trumpets, and <hi>me</hi> the grand Promoter of theſe diſturbances, and head of the Faction; all <hi>whom particularly</hi> (I ſhould not ſpeak it, were it not a moſt evident truth) were the juſt contrary to all theſe aſperſions; perſons induſtrious and in the way of thriving by it; living com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably as any there; and whoſe greateſt hopes and aſſurance of perfecting their good condition, conſiſted in that Colonyes advance, and their own continuation in it. But <hi>this</hi> is too <hi>poſitive;</hi> to deſcend therefore to Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities and <hi>manifest Illations.</hi> I ſhall firſt then deſire <hi>Byam</hi> to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that I was not ſent forth to ſatisfie the <hi>timerous Indians,</hi> but <hi>our time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſelves;</hi> 'twas <hi>we</hi> had information that the <hi>Indians,</hi> in (revenge of ſome pieces of juſtice executed on them for deteining our <hi>run-away Negros,</hi>) had deſigned to <hi>cut us off;</hi> and that great numbers of them were to <hi>that purpoſe</hi> congregated in an adjacent river: to prevent and ſuppreſſe <hi>this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> I was by order of the General Aſſembly ſent forth with <hi>general In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions</hi> to do according to <hi>neceſſity and diſcretion.</hi> Before my going, <hi>this buſineſs</hi> of <hi>Jones, Maſhart</hi> and my <hi>Brother</hi> happened, and the diſcontents in the Colony grew loud. <hi>That very night</hi> that I was to ſet forth I received a letter from <hi>Byam</hi> (which I have yet to ſhew) <hi>then</hi> a long way diſtant at a Feaſt; wherein he tells me that he had received the <hi>Report</hi> (by <hi>which</hi> the whole Colony was at that time alarm'd) that thirty of our men were alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſlain by <hi>theſe Indians;</hi> and not knowing what <hi>particular orders</hi> to give, becauſe the certainty of <hi>this</hi> as yet appeared not, he leaves the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105536:7"/>of the whole <hi>buſineſs</hi> to me, encouraging to an <hi>actual engagement</hi> if I found the rumour true, in which he promiſed well to ſecond me. Now let the impartial Reader judge, if there were a party that deſigned the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies deſtruction, if many of <hi>its</hi> boſome enemies were now with <hi>me, who</hi> am ſaid to be the head and grand Promoter of <hi>that deſign,</hi> whether a better opportunity could be preſented to us to bring all things into confuſion, and out of the general ruines to repair our own? <hi>The falling on any one town of</hi> Indians <hi>with hoſtility</hi> had in great part effected <hi>this;</hi> or if (as hereafter he laies to our charge) we had a purpoſe by force of arms to remove the power <hi>de facto,</hi> and to ſeiz <hi>his</hi> perſon, when could it better have been effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted then now? <hi>Byam</hi> was abſent, the Colony full of diſcontents and fears, I in <hi>arms</hi> with a boundleſſe Commiſſion, and (as himſelf ſaies) abetted by many of the faction. What hindred to make my train as numerous as my ſelf pleaſed, to march up to the place where <hi>Byam</hi> was, environed onely with feaſts and jollity (to which alſo I had <hi>his</hi> and the <hi>preſent occaſions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation</hi>) and to make my ſelf maſter of his perſon, and in <hi>that</hi> of the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? But when it ſhall appear that nothing of <hi>this</hi> was done or attempted by me (for if it had, either <hi>Byam</hi> would have complained of it, or elſe I ſhould <hi>now</hi> have had no cauſe to complain) that I managed this buſineſſe of the <hi>Indians</hi> with all integrity, ſatisfied <hi>their</hi> diſcontents, and removed <hi>our</hi> fears, and, having done my errand, that (notwithſtanding the threats of <hi>gallows, priſons,</hi> and <hi>irons</hi> wherewith many of the Gentlemen with me were accoſted at my return, and <hi>my ſelf</hi> thought <hi>unſafe,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſuſpected</hi>) I, yet, diſarmed my ſelf and Partizans, who all retired to their reſpective habitations; it cannot rationally be concluded but that either there was no ſuch plot as is charged on us, or, if there were, I was not of it, much leſſe the head. And <hi>this truth</hi> alſo will readily emerge, that <hi>the raiſers of it</hi> thought themſelves to have <hi>force</hi> enough of <hi>words</hi> and <hi>arguments</hi> for the preſent <hi>diſpute,</hi> and therefore needed not the <hi>force</hi> of <hi>ſwords and guns.</hi> Again, it is ſtrange, if I were the head of theſe deſigns, that ſuch eminent criminals as <hi>Maſhart, Jones,</hi> and my <hi>Brother,</hi> all <hi>then skulking</hi> for fear of <hi>Byam,</hi> did not rather repair to me, then in <hi>arms,</hi> and of <hi>better</hi> force to protect them than their <hi>ſingle weapons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the ſtory of Saint <hi>Vincents,</hi> the diſcourſe we had of it was as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as any I have ever heard or meddled in: and afterwards when <hi>Byam</hi> would needs ſqueez a plot out of it (a <hi>torture</hi> which at this time all our oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional diſcourſes ſuffered) it proved in it ſelf ſo ridiculous, improbable, nay impoſſible to be the <hi>real deſign</hi> of any but very fools or madmen; and <hi>then</hi> alſo was ſo far from menacing any harm to the Colony, or an acting contrariant to the preſent government, that after <hi>Byam</hi> had buſied himſelf
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105536:8"/>much to finde out the <hi>depth</hi> of it, and had gotten one who ſtuck not to ſwear according to <hi>his own dictamens,</hi> Captain <hi>Crook</hi> (happily by at <hi>this examination</hi>) by a clear owning and rehearſing whatever was truth in <hi>that buſineſſe</hi> quaſhed the accuſation; the main reaſon that the <hi>Reader</hi> findes it not amongſt the other <hi>annexed depoſitions: A fate</hi> which I am ſure all the calumnies againſt us would have ſuffered, had we been allowed the equity to be preſent at the ſwearing of the witneſſes. But leſt <hi>we</hi> (<hi>whom</hi> they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinied to ruine) ſhould appear too innocent for their malice, they would not, <hi>after this,</hi> ſuffer <hi>any, deſigned</hi> to exile, to make a defence, but poſted on to a ſentence; and if the priſoner but ſpoke againſt it as <hi>strange to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced and not heard, Marten and Noel</hi> would make it their admiration that they ſhould offer at a pleading <hi>not guilty.</hi> And as <hi>theſe</hi> were firſt <hi>iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erward judged to haue deſerved it (for <hi>their</hi> better impunity <hi>who had ſo uſed them</hi>) ſo <hi>one, whom</hi> they durſt not have let looſe after <hi>ſuch u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,</hi> was before he appeared, aſſured of pardon, if he would but with ſilence accept it; and when he came before them <hi>themſelves</hi> pleaded his innocence (though the <hi>leader</hi> to all the <hi>declaimed guilt</hi>) and aſſured their ready mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; which diſcourſe when he received with a <hi>bow onely,</hi> they render him as carrying himſelf with <hi>remorſe, ſubmiſſion,</hi> and <hi>civility,</hi> and <hi>therefore</hi> me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting <hi>their moderation;</hi> while the <hi>others,</hi> for claimingan equal ſhare in his <hi>innocence,</hi> are argued of <hi>impudence,</hi> and epitheted <hi>incorrigible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 8. <hi>In the mean</hi> Maſhart, Jones, Will. Sanford, <hi>and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents range to and again by ſtealth, corrupting and provoking the people a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the authority, alledging there was no ſuch</hi> Proclamation <hi>from his</hi> Majeſty, <hi>and that there could be no power over them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. Admit all this be true (for as yet we finde no <hi>proof</hi> thereof) I cannot but <hi>now</hi> call it diſcretion to inform the people (who were by the intended convention to become <hi>parties</hi>) of the <hi>true ſtate</hi> of the <hi>queſtion.</hi> Yet ſo little was I hitherto engaged in <hi>this diſpute,</hi> that <hi>none of theſe</hi> in the leaſt conſulted me: for though I was ſatisfied that the General Aſſemblies pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was an uſurpation, yet I had no thoughts of oppoſing or forcibly remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them; and therefore <hi>within my ſelf</hi> condemned theſe <hi>ſtrivings,</hi> not as <hi>criminal</hi> but <hi>indiſcreet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 9. <hi>I was daily acquainted with all their motions, actions, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and could at any time have taken them by force, but remitted it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the General Convention of the Free-holders, which upon</hi> ſerious advice <hi>I had ſummoned as well as the General Aſſembly: who were to meet on the</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> November.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105536:8"/>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. <hi>This</hi> I readily believe, knowing it the grand complaint in that Colony that <hi>Olivers policies</hi> were daily practiſed, and no ſociety or ſcarce family found empty of an <hi>Informer</hi> or <hi>Trapanner: one incitement</hi> to many hot ſpirits to <hi>ſpeak</hi> worſe then they <hi>thought.</hi> The worſt of <hi>ſlaveries!</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the honour, fortune, and life of the ingenious to the mercy of knaves and fools; <hi>ſuch</hi> as by <hi>theſe very practices</hi> evidence themſelves dead to all ſenſe of honour and honeſty. <hi>Byam,</hi> when he takes occaſion, a little while after, to mention <hi>my letter,</hi> might have remembred that I condemned, and dehorted from theſe kind of ſubtilties, whereby the <hi>innocent</hi> and the <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> are more often enſnared then the more <hi>wary criminals.</hi> But I wonder what Law he hath found for acting by <hi>force?</hi> he muſt take it from ſome new precedents of the <hi>late uſurpers,</hi> for I am ſure our <hi>old law</hi> diſapproves and puniſhes it. The <hi>ſerious advice</hi> on which he ſummoned all the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders to meet at one place I gueſſe to be this, he feared if he admitted the regular way <hi>[of each diviſion chuſing their proper repreſentatives]</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>few</hi> of <hi>his own diviſion</hi> he ſhould hardly finde <hi>votes enough</hi> for himſelf to be continued <hi>one,</hi> and conſequently muſt deſpair of being gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for that year; he would therefore rather venture his greatneſſe on the more numerous chances of the multitude drawn into one body: for <hi>elſe,</hi> it was without precedent, and a ſoleciſm in reaſon too, (eſpecially at ſuch time as <hi>[to avoid their unneceſsary trouble]</hi> was the main excuſe for <hi>taking away the peoples priviledges</hi>) to call all the inhabitants, diſperſed many ſcores of miles, to <hi>one place,</hi> in a <hi>tumultuous manner</hi> to confirm or renew <hi>their government.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. <hi>At</hi> Lieutenant Col. Sanfords <hi>return of his</hi> party <hi>they enquire whether</hi> Maſhart <hi>and</hi> Jones <hi>are impriſoned, and gave out publickly had they found them committed they would have torne the Priſon in pieces; another ſwore he would break the neck of the Colony, or his own neck, in ſix moneths; another would kill the Marſhal, with other most impudent rants and menaces of theſe Rumbullion Hectors.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 10. When I returned it was told us the Governour had garriſon'd his houſe, kept parties in boats upon the river, made a Sedulous queſt for <hi>Maſhart, Jones</hi> and my <hi>Brother,</hi> for <hi>whom agallows</hi> was preparing, and <hi>Irons</hi> for divers other Gentlemen then in armes with me. They told us that I was voic't the original of theſe tumults with deſigne of making my ſelf Governour (one of the many arrows which <hi>Byam</hi> and his <hi>Partiſans</hi> had frequently ſhot to wound my reputation with the people, and render me
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105536:9"/>leſſe eligible into publick affaires, where my <hi>honeſty</hi> was moſt commonly irkſome, becauſe moſt conſtantly counter to their <hi>different</hi> practiſes:) <hi>theſe reports</hi> kindled a flame in the Gentlemen with me; who, prizing their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and honour, were deeply affected with the menace of a <hi>Confinement proper to rogues:</hi> and being well ſatisfied in that point [<hi>that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> &amp;c. <hi>had no legal Power</hi>] they ſtuck not publickly to <hi>aſſert it,</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> could not, but as <hi>Treſpaſſers,</hi> act a violence againſt their perſons <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>hence</hi> it is not unlikely but ſome might threaten to tear down the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or kill the Marſhal, viz. If they ſhould either be ſhut up in the <hi>one,</hi> or ſeized by the <hi>other.</hi> And probable it is that in theſe heats <hi>Crook</hi> might ſay <hi>he would break the Colony,</hi> inferring that <hi>others</hi> ſhould ſhare in the <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine</hi> with <hi>which</hi> they meditated to depreſſe <hi>him;</hi> for, <hi>verba ſemper accipienda ſunt in mitiori ſenſu.</hi> But admit theſe words were abſolute, without any <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> or other <hi>excitement</hi> then the ſpeakers <hi>malice,</hi> they are at worſt but evidence of an <hi>endeavour</hi> without <hi>effect.</hi> And 'tis an Impudent <hi>begging the queſtion</hi> to call them <hi>ſeditious</hi> and <hi>rebellious;</hi> for <hi>thoſe termes</hi> preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a <hi>legal Authority</hi> againſt <hi>whom this</hi> was uttered; and <hi>that</hi> was <hi>it</hi> in diſpute, and ſhould not be taken for <hi>granted,</hi> till <hi>conceded</hi> by the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, convinced by <hi>force</hi> of <hi>arguments</hi> not armes. But the ſworded man <hi>takes</hi> and <hi>leaves</hi> at his pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. <hi>After this</hi> Lieutenant Col. Sanford <hi>ſends me an accompt of his voyage, admiring at the ſtrange diſſentions and rumours which he found at his return, profeſſing his innocency and integrity which I really credited. But the report that I had ſummoned the whole Countrey in, and theſe male-contents deſpairing of compaſſing their aimes (obſerving the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Countrey bent againſt them) they plotted afreſh: for in this Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of time arrived three ſhips from</hi> Guinea, <hi>two with Negroes under the command of</hi> Captain Nicholas Sulke <hi>(who would diſpoſe none till he ſaw the Authority ſettled) the third belonging to</hi> Captain John Bonner, <hi>an empty veſſel who had been taken by the</hi> Dutch <hi>in</hi> Guinea. <hi>Theſe</hi> Deſperadoes <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately meaſuring</hi> his <hi>condition by</hi> their own, <hi>thought him a proper Inſtrument for their purpoſe, &amp; therefore ſent and treated with him to fraight him for</hi> Jamaica, <hi>proffering him fifty thouſand pounds of Sugar to carry them, their Negroes, and ſuch things as they ſhould bring aboard, off the Countrey.</hi> Captain Bonner <hi>was attentive to their Propoſals, till they told him of ſtanding upon their guard, and defending what ſhould be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into his ſhip; to which in ſhort he told them he was not a perſon for their</hi> turn, <hi>they were miſtaken in him, that he never</hi> did <hi>nor ever</hi> would <hi>ſell any Port, that without the Governours order he would carry none off,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105536:9"/>if</hi> that <hi>were brought he would readily ſerve them</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but by the by, fifty thouſand pounds of Sugar was more by fifty times then the treaters with him were worth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. Though I found my ſelf not exempted the liſt of Delinquents, and well knew from former experience that <hi>Byam</hi> wanted onely occaſion, not malice to proſecute me with an exemplar ſeverity; yet would I not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently unfix thoſe reſolutions of <hi>indifferency and moderation,</hi> which in this preſent diſpute I had put on. Having therefore milded thoſe paſſions which <hi>theſe rumours</hi> had raiſed in the Gentlemen of my party, I perſwaded them 1. To diſcredit thoſe improbable reports. 2. with a ſtill patience to attend the deſigned convention of the people (where I doubted not the calming all things by a moderate debate and mutual condeſcention) and 3. To diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and retire to their ſeveral homes. Succeſsfull in <hi>this,</hi> I laboured the <hi>like</hi> with <hi>Byam;</hi> and after I had given him an accompt of my voyage, I recounted the various reports which alarm'd us at our return. The <hi>innocence</hi> I profeſſed was <hi>this,</hi> 1. That I had no aims at the government; for the truth of <hi>which</hi> I atteſted heaven; and deſired him, when all the Free-holders met, to examine them ſingly upon oath whether ever I had made any kinde of attempts on any <hi>one</hi> of them for <hi>their votes:</hi> and for his further ſecurity I offered to become obliged by all Bonds, religious or civil, never to accept <hi>it</hi> though thereunto courted by the united Colony. 2. I aſſured him that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver promoted the preſent diſputes made againſt the authority, and was hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſorry that they were begun. But withall he may remember that 3. I told him I was ever perſwaded that if any durſt queſtion the powers legality he would be <hi>by reaſon</hi> unanſwerable: and therefore I entreated him, ſince matters were in <hi>the preſent state,</hi> to proceed by moderate juſtifiable ways, and not <hi>ſo</hi> as he had begun with <hi>Jones,</hi> in <hi>which</hi> I could not abet him <hi>ſalva virtute &amp; juſtitia.</hi> 4. I blamed the violent counſels of <hi>Marten,</hi> who offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf the Hangman of any at the Governours ſingle command; of <hi>Vſher,</hi> who adviſed and threatned to nip them in the bud; and of <hi>Ferris,</hi> to hold their noſes to the grind-ſtone: <hi>menaces</hi> fitter to <hi>frighten</hi> the Colony into a <hi>diſſolution,</hi> then to <hi>work</hi> a <hi>conſolidation.</hi> Much of this letter may appear from <hi>Byams</hi> anſwer which I can produce. If now by what he ſaith of my profeſſions of innocency, he would have the world believe that I did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſelf clearly and abſolutely of his party, approving all his actions, my own Letter, if he dare ſhew it, will contradict him: and let both our future actions be compared with our Letters, It will appear, <hi>I was conſtant in my perſwaſions, and eſteem of Juſtice, while he varied his reſolutions and brake his word.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105536:10"/>
               <p>But it's ſtrange that thoſe whom he calls Deſperadoes ſhould enter upon a treatment with <hi>Bonner, needy and empty,</hi> to do God knows what; when at the ſame time <hi>Sulke,</hi> fam'd <hi>rich</hi> in gold, <hi>full</hi> of Negroes, <hi>weak</hi> for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>diſtruſtleſs</hi> of ſuch attempts, gave all the invitations to <hi>needy men</hi> to caſt conſcience and danger at their backs <hi>in his ſurprize:</hi> whatever the deſigne was which they would have drawn <hi>Bonner</hi> to, it ſeems it had <hi>perill</hi> in it, and muſt by <hi>force</hi> have been defended; and ſo might <hi>ſuch an attempt on Sulke</hi> have been: nor can any thing be objected to <hi>this action,</hi> which would not have equally ſorted to <hi>that.</hi> But how comes it that <hi>this</hi> is here mentioned as a plot of us Exiles, and nothing thereof charged to us at our reckoning? In all the Depoſitions I finde not one ſyllable of this, (nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ever heard of it before I ſaw <hi>this his Declaration</hi> in <hi>England</hi>) and therefore am ready to think, if any ſuch thing were in agitation, it was ſome engine of <hi>Byams;</hi> which (though it failed of drawing inconſiderate perſons into the action, yet) might at leaſt give <hi>ſome ſuſpition</hi> of a <hi>Plot:</hi> (and to be <hi>ſuſpected,</hi> with them was to be guilty.) An art not unuſed <hi>even there.</hi> And poſſibly had he brought the <hi>accuſation</hi> into publick while we were preſent, the miſtery of iniquity had been diſcovered. However, <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> is now here, and doth not accuſe <hi>us that were ſent off</hi> with this matter; If <hi>ſuch treaters</hi> were, 'tis moſt likely they are <hi>kept behinde,</hi> as fitter for <hi>Byams uſe</hi> then <hi>our company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what may we think this new plot to be? at firſt ſight it looks like the attempts of <hi>thoſe</hi> that are weary of their creditours company, and then ſome of <hi>his eminent aſſeſſors</hi> may be ſuſpected rather then <hi>we:</hi> (and indeed <hi>his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding mark</hi> beſt ſuits with ſome of <hi>them.</hi>) At plaineſt, it is a <hi>running away</hi> from the countrey, not a <hi>ſtaying in it,</hi> working its <hi>confuſion by a disjointing of the Authority,</hi> with which he taxeth us a little before: but the <hi>Gentleman</hi> is gotten into a <hi>wood of plots,</hi> and being loſt in the <hi>mazes</hi> of his <hi>own invention,</hi> he untreads his <hi>former ſteps,</hi> and wants <hi>a thread of truth</hi> to guide him out.</p>
               <p>Yet grant him all this likewiſe; I would fain have him ſatisfie us <hi>what law</hi> it is that puniſheth <hi>[this peculiar endeavour]</hi> with trial by an <hi>arbitrary military court,</hi> and a cenſure of <hi>irons, fine, and baniſhment?</hi> the thoughts of the heart not reduced into practiſe, though never ſo evident, are not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictable, except in that onely caſe <hi>of imagining the Kings death,</hi> which the the Statute hath made Treaſon. And ſuppoſe <hi>bare endeavours</hi> were penal, I have not yet found any repeal of that ſacred ſanction in Magna Charta <hi>[no freeman ſhall be taken, impriſoned, diſſeiſed, outlaw'd, exiled, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe deſtroyed or condemned without tryal by his Peers or the Law.]</hi> Whence alſo had they their Commiſſion for erecting a Martial Court? (if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105536:10"/>we ſhould grant them the <hi>Proclamation.</hi>) Both <hi>King and Parliament</hi> have <hi>expreſly</hi> ſaid that <hi>no ſuch Commiſſions ſhall hereafter iſſue forth.</hi> I dare promiſe that the <hi>Authours</hi> both for <hi>their ruling, and thus ruling,</hi> will upon enquiry be found <hi>onely themſelves</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. This project <hi>failing, they attempt a</hi> ſecond, <hi>viz. the ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zal of a ſmall Shallop of ten Tuns, belonging in part to</hi> Cryn Jacobſon <hi>a</hi> Dutchman, <hi>who came from fiſhing with ſome Fiſh and Manates. This</hi> Cryn <hi>lived here before the</hi> Engliſh <hi>ſettled, &amp; hath ſubmitted unto, &amp; lived under, the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government; by the Act of the Countrey was made free, hath been a very great help to our ſettlement, is partner both in Shallop and Plantation with an</hi> Engliſh-<hi>man, and employed his Veſſel on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in fiſhing for the good of the Colony. But the ſeizing this Veſſel as a Prize for his Majeſty they deſigned as a mask, and arm and congregate themſelves againſt his Majeſties Power, which</hi> their own confeſſion <hi>doth manifeſt. On the</hi> 23. <hi>of</hi> Novemb. <hi>Captain</hi> Thomas Crook <hi>(an old Soldier, fitter to execute than contrive) with Captain</hi> George Straunge, <hi>Mr.</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Maſhart, <hi>Mr.</hi> Rowland Bulkley, <hi>Mr.</hi> Thomas Archer <hi>and others, entred this Shallop, having two Men and a Boy aboard her.</hi> Crook <hi>in the firſt place burns one of the Sea-men in the breast with a light Match, to extort a confeſſion where the Ammunition lay, which he diſcovered: in the next place he plundered their Cheſts, and divided what he found amongſt his Officers which he had made. Captain</hi> Straunge <hi>was ſent abroad to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure what men, arms, &amp; ammunition he could poſſible; about ſeven pounds of powder, ſome ball, and fire-locks he immediately ſent aboard with his Negroes, and in the night followed with Mr.</hi> William Needham, <hi>Mr.</hi> William Sanford, <hi>Mr.</hi> Peter Fabian <hi>armed: And when they had fixed and charged their arms,</hi> Crook <hi>vaunted</hi> [now we are ready to talk with the Governour.]</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 12. <hi>Doloſus verſatur in Generalibus,</hi> and though <hi>Byam</hi> cannot define what the evil of taking this Shallop is, yet it muſt be a <hi>nefarious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> the proſecuting of a wicked deſign, ſo <hi>horrid,</hi> that his mouth is filled with the very <hi>name</hi> of it, and cannot pronounce the <hi>thing.</hi> But becauſe he ſeems to be at a loſſe to determine what ends ſix or ſeven unarmed men could have, in publickly ſeizing a ſmall Shallop of inconſiderable value, up in the heart of the River, and there remaining with the poſſeſſion of her; I will undeceive the world with the whole ſtory of that action, which <hi>Byam</hi> portions out (as he doth our words alſo) by ſuch pieces as beſt ſize with his purpoſe. Thoſe Gentlemen then here named, were in company
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105536:11"/>with Mr. <hi>Wroth;</hi> (whom I wonder ſhould be left out, being the <hi>ring-lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> in this action to the reſt) their diſcourſe was of what was then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon talk, <hi>the preſentidiſputes againſt the Government,</hi> and what beſt courſe might be taken to make <hi>Byam</hi> ſhew <hi>authority</hi> for his continuing Governour. <hi>Wroth</hi> hereupon adviſeth to ſeize this Veſſel (whoſe owners and Sailers were <hi>Dutch,</hi> and who unluckily lay in their Eye) as a prize to his Majeſty. A Court, ſaith he, muſt be called to try the King's Title, we will plead to the Juriſdiction of that Court, and thereby draw <hi>Byam</hi> either to ſhew the <hi>Proclamation</hi> he boaſts of, or elſe to confeſſs himſelf to have no ſuch thing. The <hi>Council</hi> was approved, and in the poſture they were, (which was without all kind of furniture for any <hi>other deſign</hi>) they go aboard this Boat, take her as his Majeſties prize, put two of the Sea-men aſhore, and one they let remain aboard to ſee that nothing be Embezeled. Captain <hi>Straunge</hi> is deſired to acquaint my Brother (dwelling hard by) with <hi>this action,</hi> that he might go and conſult with Mr. <hi>Wroth</hi> about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging the <hi>intended Plea,</hi> becauſe he had ſeen the late <hi>Act of Parliament concerning Trade,</hi> on <hi>which</hi> they purpoſed to proſecute this Veſſel, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their ſeizure: this was the occaſion of my Brother's comming to them, armed only with his Sword, whoſate a while on the ſide of the Shallop, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining diſcourſes with Mr. <hi>Wroth,</hi> &amp; then returned home. <hi>Straunge</hi> in this mean while goes to <hi>Crooks</hi> and his own houſe, &amp; fetches thence two or three Carbines and a Piſtol, &amp; ſome ſmall ammunition; rather to ſecure the prize from a being re-taken by the owners, &amp; <hi>themſelves</hi> from a being ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly cudgelled out of her by the Sea-men, then with any hopes with ſo ſmall a force to oppoſe <hi>Byam</hi> &amp; the <hi>generality of the Colony,</hi> which (as <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> ſaith a little before) <hi>themſelves</hi> had obſerved to be bent againſt them. After this <hi>Straunge</hi> returns, accompanied with <hi>Needham</hi> and <hi>Fabian,</hi> who co-habited in the ſame houſe with him. M. <hi>Wroth</hi> had this day appointed <hi>Banister</hi> to come and receive ſome Coppers which he had ſold him, and fearing leaſt <hi>Banister</hi> ſhould paſſe by unſeen and miſſe of him, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to hale all Boats that came up with the Flood, which they did till they found <hi>Banister,</hi> with whom Mr. <hi>Wroth</hi> went home. Mr. <hi>Maſhart</hi> returned alſo aſhore again, it being reſolved upon, to leave no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the Shallop than might ſerve to keep the poſſeſſion of her. As to the other Bug-bear actions and ſpeeches, I ſhall take occaſion to ſpeak to them when I examine the Depoſitions.</p>
               <p>All this I learned from Mr <hi>Wroth</hi> and my Brother, at ſuch time as their viſits were permitted; for as yet I had not intermingled with any thing they call <hi>Sedition.</hi> And here now the <hi>Reader</hi> hath a cleer view of this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the very inſide of it; let him compare this Relation with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105536:11"/>Teſtimonies, and trace it with the ſevereſt ſcrutiny of reaſon, if he can find a worſe, or other intention in it than what is here declared. But ſay they had worſe intentions, they were ineffectuall; and had they had a full and miſchievous effect, I doe not yet find that <hi>Byam</hi> and his accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices could legally judge either actions or intentions. If it be ſaid, that then none could, and conſequently the Colony was in a miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; I grant that too, but <hi>fault</hi> none but <hi>Byam</hi> and his <hi>Partiſans</hi> for drawing on <hi>that miſery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what would <hi>Byam</hi> inferre from the enumeration of all theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in behalf of <hi>Cryn?</hi> that his Shallop was <hi>no Prize?</hi> alaſs! that is not the Diſpute, but whether ſhe might without a <hi>horrid crime</hi> be ſeized as a Prize or not; and whether, being ſeized, his Majeſty ought not to have had a legal tryal for her? Had <hi>Byam</hi> called a legal, or only a formal Court, to take judicial cognizance of this caſe, he would not have been much put to it for arguments to defend <hi>Cryns</hi> title; for the <hi>ſeizers</hi> purpoſed not to urge <hi>that point</hi> ſo ſeverely to <hi>his prejudice,</hi> after they had been once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the <hi>Courts Authority and Juriſdiction:</hi> and <hi>this</hi> may appear from what is witneſſed that <hi>Crook</hi> ſhould ſay: <hi>[I value not my part of this prize at a pipe of Tobacco, 'tis another buſineſse we are come about concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countrey, and the chuſing a new Governour.]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. <hi>Theſe rebellious acts of Felony and hoſtility were no ſooner committed, but I had immediately advice thereof, (though at that time five leagues from them) as alſo of their intentions to r'ally what force poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible they could, to guard the River, and keep Boats from paſſing to the meeting (which was to be about four dayes after) to ſeize my Perſon, to bring all things into confuſion, the better to compaſſe their ends. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeriouſly conſidering the danger of delays, I forthwith commanded Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major</hi> Geo. Uſher <hi>with a</hi> Periago <hi>man'd, with strict orders, if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to regain the Shallop-peaceably, if not, by force: and at the ſame time I raiſed all the upper parts of the Countrey and followed to his aſſistance. But in my way I encountered my</hi> Major <hi>returning, who gave me</hi> this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt; <hi>that he found</hi> twelve men <hi>in armes aboard, that they required him to keep off from the Veſſel, being all in a warlike poſture; that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them in his Majeſties name from me to deliver up the Veſſel, which they refuſed; that he ſurrounded her ſeveral times, and told them he would permit none to come aſhore from her, or go aboard to her; that they, fearing my ſudden approach to re-inforce him, after ſome debate ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred her up; that they were gone to</hi> Caſſiapoory <hi>with their arms and ammunition.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:105536:12"/>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Sect. 13. By the Epithets he gives to this lawfull and juſtifiable action, may be ſeen how far every of <hi>Byams</hi> accuſations is to be credited without examination: But to the point. I will believe <hi>his Mercury's</hi> nimble enough, &amp; affirm ſome of them rode on the wings of the <hi>aire,</hi> the <hi>aire</hi> I mean, of <hi>his own fancy:</hi> &amp; thoſe were <hi>they</hi> that brought him the immediate intelligence of theſe Gentlemens <hi>intentions,</hi> &amp; were I ſuppoſe the ſame that brought the <hi>former advice of his Majesties Proclamation.</hi> And becauſe the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vouchſafes to come forth of his <hi>cloud of Generals,</hi> and expoſe himſelf to <hi>view,</hi> we will a while <hi>ſurvey</hi> him. And firſt, <hi>what ends</hi> ſhould theſe men have in endeavouring to guard the River, and keep Boats from paſſing to the <hi>meeting,</hi> ſince <hi>themſelves</hi> waited for <hi>that meeting?</hi> Is it likely that any men in their wits ſhould ſeize a heavy Shallop, unable to move, (had ſhe been unmor'd, which ſhe never was) but as acted by the ſtream or a chanceable wind, with her to r'ally what poſſible force to guard the River? From what quarter too ſhould they fetch theſe forces? the whole Colony are ſaid to be againſt them. If they had hopes for ſuch intents, they were themſelves Maſters of <hi>Periagoes</hi> ſuſceptible of <hi>ten times the force,</hi> with which they could have moved into all quarters with an <hi>activity and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> requiſite to ſuch a deſign, and have ſeized <hi>Byams</hi> perſon (or attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at leaſt) at home in his own houſe, and not ridiculouſly have ſent him an <hi>alarm</hi> four and twenty hours before, and waited his comming at their ſtation five leagues diſtance, with hopes <hi>then</hi> to take him <hi>when</hi> he centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled their ſtrength, and had coopt them up within their <hi>wooden walls.</hi> I wonder he had not contrived their plot for them <hi>thus,</hi> that they determi-to have <hi>Byam</hi> come aboard to them, and deliver himſelf up: or <hi>thus,</hi> that they were reſolved that <hi>he</hi> ſhould call none to <hi>his guard</hi> but who were of <hi>their faction,</hi> and ſhould betray him unto them: for the manner which they uſed in carrying on this deſign which he chargeth them with, points at ſome <hi>ſuch ſtrange hope,</hi> or elſe (which is the more likely truth) they had indeed <hi>no ſuch purpoſe at all.</hi> But how comes he here to ſay, <hi>they would keep Boats from the meeting,</hi> both when the ſixth part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey were not to paſſe <hi>that way,</hi> and when in the Depoſitions (to which he gives ſuch uncontrovertible credit) <hi>Crook</hi> is accuſed <hi>himſelf</hi> to purpoſe a repair to the <hi>meeting,</hi> to try whether they would make the Shallop a Prize or not? How is it too, that even now they were preſented <hi>as running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and, having gotten wings, they fix themſelves into a <hi>ſtanding guard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though where <hi>Uſher</hi> is known there be no great credit given to his words or oaths; and though he here commit a great miſtake in telling <hi>twelve</hi> for <hi>ſeven,</hi> (fear frequently multiplies the object) yet we will not diſpute the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105536:12"/>
                  <hi>verity</hi> of his <hi>relation</hi> to his <hi>Patroòn;</hi> but onely affirm, that they that had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Prize were before determined to deliver her up to <hi>Byams</hi> order up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the firſt ſummons; (the reaſon that ſeveral were already gone from her) <hi>Crook</hi> onely, with a ſouldiers bravery, was deſirous to try whither <hi>Byam,</hi> or any by his command, durſt act hoſtility againſt <hi>them that</hi> declared themſelves to ſtand there in defence of his Majeſties Shallop: and upon <hi>that ſcore</hi> it was that he ſaid when he charged the guns (not <hi>[now we are ready to talk with the Governour]</hi> but, as in the Depoſitions) <hi>now I wiſh the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour would come and ſpeak with us.</hi> In purſuance of <hi>this councel</hi> alſo was the ſhallop firſt refuſed to <hi>Uſher;</hi> they onely waiting the effects of his <hi>braving rounds:</hi> nor did they at laſt deliver her <hi>for fear of Byams re-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement</hi> (of which there was great need, indeed, againſt ſeaven men and a long-boat) for <hi>ſome</hi> of them were reſolved <hi>to try him too</hi> as well as <hi>his Aga;</hi> but <hi>others</hi> (fearing they ſhould not make ſo clear and evident a juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the harmleſſeneſs of this action, by their voluntary ſurrender of the ſhallop, if they deferred it till <hi>Byams</hi> approach, when they might ſeem rather inforc't to it) purſued the <hi>former councel;</hi> and, aſſoon as <hi>Uſher</hi> was gone ſhore, followed him and delivered up the veſſel to him; taking <hi>his</hi> had <hi>and faith</hi> that ſhe ſhould remain in notion of a <hi>prize</hi> till a legal court <hi>word</hi> determined the queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 14. <hi>The Countrey being up and very unwilling to retire home till theſe diſturbers of their peace were ſecured, earnestly deſired (to which I as readily condeſcended) that theſe enemies to our King and Countrey might be ſpeedily apprehended; which in honour and duty I was bound to ſee performed, had it not been ſo ſeriouſly requested. And therefore that night I ſent Captain</hi> Auguſtine Story <hi>with a party of fire-locks, who found moſt of this ſeditious gang together; whom he diſarmed and brought away, as alſo their arms and ammunition: theſe</hi> (<hi>with ſome other of the</hi> confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy <hi>whom I had ſurprized a little before) I committed under a guard till the meeting of the</hi> General Aſſembly, <hi>which was to be about four days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The next day I writ a very civil letter to</hi> Lieutenant Collonel <hi>Sanford (who was of my council) adviſing him of all occurrences and tranſastions, and deſired his company and advice in theſe diſtempers: but he, being net<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled that his complices were under reſtraint, inſtead of obſerving my orders repairs immediately to them, and first commanded Captain</hi> Story <hi>(who had then command of the guard) to lay down his armes; to whom</hi> he <hi>made anſwer that he could not do it without my order;</hi> Sanford <hi>ſaid he was</hi> his Superior Officer, <hi>and therefore he ought to obey him;</hi> Story <hi>retorted that he was placed there by</hi> him <hi>that was</hi> Superiour <hi>to them</hi> both: <hi>whereupon</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105536:13"/>
                  <hi>flies to the houſe where the priſoners were, commanded them all forth and told them if they had courage they ſhould follow him and he would stand by them with his life and fortunes. But</hi> Captain Story <hi>(a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not to be bafled) cauſed them to retire, and preſently adviſed me of the impudent paſſages of this inſolent and imperious perſon. Haſtening to the guard I found all quiet, and told</hi> Sanford <hi>I admired at what he had done, who anſwered that it was against law in time of peace to keep any under reſtraint by force of armes; to whom I replyed, that if in time of peace men aſſumed armes against the Authority, it was lawfull and requiſite to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſuch by force of armes, and guard them with armes till they came to a tryal, and withall I charged him as a</hi> traitour and an enemy to our ſoveraign Lord the King, <hi>and committed him to the reſt of the conſpiracy: where he vomited ſuch pickled language from the brine of his paſſion as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the</hi> Rhetorick <hi>of</hi> Belinsgate; <hi>which cauſed me to remove him, from a convenient quarter, to aboard the Shallop: where the continuance of the ſcurrility of his tongue enforced me (through the Complaint of ſeveral) to deny him the ſociety of any (for a time) except his wife.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. I believe <hi>his excitements</hi> from the Countrey (who he ſays de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired this) will, upon ſearch, be found <hi>as ſlender</hi> as the <hi>concernments of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and duty</hi> which impulſed him to the following <hi>diſhonourable, unjust, and malicious proſecutions.</hi> But becauſe he tells the manner of his ſeizing us with too much advantage to himſelf, I ſhall give the <hi>Reader</hi> a more pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual account of it. On Sunday the 24. of <hi>November</hi> towards night <hi>Byam</hi> moves downward, and in the way meets Mr. <hi>Maſhart</hi> going home, whom he cauſeth his ſouldiers to lay hold on and keep priſoner. The night was come on before he came ſo low as my Brothers, and a party is commanded to beſet his chamber and take him, which they did, finding him alone and abed: thence he ſends <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> to Collonel <hi>Elyes</hi> (who knowing nothing of the Shallop, had no crime but hoſpitality, and denying to declare the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of his land) he findes him aſleep alſo, and without company (ſave thoſe of his family) yet leads him away priſoner. <hi>Story</hi> marches to Mr. <hi>Wroths</hi> (whether the Gentlemen that had ſurrendred the prize were retired, till Sunday, on which our law interdicted travelling, were over) findes the reſt, that <hi>Byam</hi> bent againſt, there, but aſleep; he wakens and acquaints them with the Governours orders, to <hi>which</hi> they readily yielded themſelves. The ſouldiers hunted for arms and ammunition every where, but found none but what <hi>neceſſity</hi> and the <hi>law</hi> warranted and allowed; which <hi>yet</hi> they carried away, <hi>more feloniouſly</hi> then <hi>the others ſeized the Shallop. Byam</hi> that night ſends away <hi>Uſher</hi> to raiſe the lower diviſions alſo into arms, thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105536:13"/>not yet ſecure enough againſt half a ſcore diſarmed captives. On Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before day I was rouzed by a meſſenger from the priſoners, who gave me a particular relation of all our proceedings, and that (from ſome words of <hi>Uſhers</hi>) they were aſſured that it was decreed to try them by a Court of War, in which <hi>Maſhart</hi> and my <hi>Brother,</hi> at feweſt, would be condemned to death. This was the firſt knowledge I had of theſe paſſages; and let it not ſeem ſtrange that I was tranſported with the apprehenſion of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger a <hi>Brother and friend</hi> were in, whom I knew guiltleſſe even as to bonds. This news is ſeconded with <hi>Byams letter,</hi> aggravating their fact with ſwelling words, and menacing a puniſhment conform to his <hi>prejudice.</hi> I had preſently a thouſand diverſities of thoughts, all tending to ſecure theſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents from <hi>Byams</hi> homeſt blows. <hi>I</hi> had frequently experimented in <hi>Jones</hi>'s caſe and others, that <hi>no plea, no ſhewing of law,</hi> would prevail with <hi>Byam</hi> and <hi>Marten</hi> to alter their determination of <hi>arbitrarily proceeding</hi> againſt ſuch as they had deſigned the <hi>examples</hi> of their <hi>revenge;</hi> and all the reſt of the <hi>General Aſsembly</hi> were either <hi>byaſſed by intereſt,</hi> or elſe <hi>ignorant of law and reaſon too,</hi> and had <hi>therefore</hi> ſuch dread and eſteem of <hi>thoſe two,</hi> that they durſt not preſume to <hi>think contrariant to their ſentence.</hi> In my <hi>advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> therefore I had no hopes to ſtead them, though the ſecond in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity both civil and martial. Yet the danger that threatned them was of <hi>that kinde,</hi> that I durſt not hazard them to the ſufferance of it. What did therefore offer it ſelf <hi>moſt preſently</hi> to my fancy I reſolved to put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (having but little <hi>diſcourſing time</hi> left me) and <hi>that was,</hi> before <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> whole ſtrength was come together, to make tryal of my power as a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, thereby, and with that intereſt I had in the command of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to remove the priſoners from under their preſent reſtraint to a place remote from the reach of <hi>Byams</hi> fury, at which diſtance we might contend with the <hi>leſse bestial</hi> weapons, <hi>arguments and reaſon,</hi> and capitulate for our return and ſafety. The preſent <hi>ſtreight</hi> affairs were in might urge to <hi>a leſs ponderated attempt, raſhneſs</hi> being often more excuſable in <hi>ſuch contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> than <hi>dull coldneſs,</hi> and more frequently crowned in the event. When I came therefore to the Guards, and found <hi>Story</hi> deaf to my deſires of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting his charge to me, and regardleſſe of my promiſes to have them forthcoming to a legal tryal, I aſſaulted him with commands as his ſuperiour officer, and finding ſhews of reſiſtance, I bade the priſoners, if they had yet any courage left, to follow me, and I would lead them through the guards.</p>
               <p>But ſome of themſelves (overruled I ſuppoſe by their fears) deſired me firſt to ſend and ſpeak with <hi>Byam;</hi> which I unluckily (not without <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticks</hi> of my felt-ſufferings) aſſented to. Thus <hi>fear</hi> of my <hi>friends dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> made me <hi>fearleſs</hi> of <hi>my own,</hi> and for onely labouring to preſerve <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105536:14"/>from an unjuſt violence, and <hi>the laws</hi> (to which I was ſvvorn) from a forcible ſubverſion, I muſt fall under the infamy of <hi>treaſon,</hi> more rightly due to <hi>them that acted the perſecution</hi> from which I was <hi>flaying.</hi> For when <hi>Byam</hi> landed, he and <hi>Noel</hi> charged me as a Traytour to his Majeſty, boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>[this was it he had a long, time aimed at.]</hi> I made my appeal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently for <hi>England,</hi> where (I told him) <hi>Treaſon</hi> was onely to be tryed; but he ſaid [I ſhould finde he would try me there]: to which I anſwered, <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther me</hi> he might, <hi>tryal</hi> it could not be called; and turning to the people, I tole them that <hi>that man</hi> in the white doublet (pointing to <hi>Byam</hi>) had no power, and therefore could not juſtifie them for abetting thoſe illegalities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us. And whatever the law ſhould determine his crime to be, when he had finiſhed his purpoſe on us, whether treaſon or murther, they were all guilty of the ſame for ſtanding by and comforting him therein: And this was the <hi>Belinsgate-language</hi> wherewith he chargeth me; and for ſuch kinde of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcourſe I was afterward confined a board that fatal Shallop, where when I ſhewed to ſeveral ſtrangers, viſiters, the laſt Commiſſion <hi>Byam</hi> had from he <hi>Delegates,</hi> and how long ſince his power was determined, <hi>Uſher</hi> was ſent aboard, commanded my company and papers away, and me to be kept in the ſtinking cloſe hold of the Shallop, where none was to ſee or ſpeak with me: nor would they ſuffer me to keep the ſtatutes of <hi>England,</hi> but took <hi>them</hi> away alſo and carried them to <hi>Byam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But grant that I railed in the <hi>Idiom of an oyſter-wench,</hi> it can be at worſt but an <hi>incivility;</hi> and ſuch a kinde of <hi>indiſcretion</hi> in me, as it is in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who, over-cholerick at his <hi>loſs, &amp;c. rails</hi> at the <hi>robbers</hi> while he is yet in their power; the world by a <hi>common irony</hi> may ſay <hi>[he deſerved the ill uſage he ſuffered for having leſs moderation at ſuch a time]</hi> but I think none will conclude the <hi>inflictions</hi> of the <hi>robbers, juſtice;</hi> nor will it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for <hi>them</hi> when they come to the <hi>Bar</hi> to ſay, <hi>we bound and gagged him becauſe he ſhould not proclaim our theft and call in defence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 15. <hi>On the</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> November, <hi>the</hi> General Aſſembly <hi>being ſate, I ſent for Collonel</hi> Chriſtopher Legard, <hi>Captain</hi> Charls Legard, <hi>and Captain</hi> Nicholas Sulke, <hi>who were in</hi> England <hi>at the happy revolution; and did there declare and aver that they had ſeen and heard</hi> his Majeſties Proclamation <hi>for the continuance of all Governours, Magistrates,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I then cauſed all the inhabitants then preſent to be drawn up, to whom I declar'd the cauſe of their convention, the authours of our diſturbances, the drift of their deſigns, their rebellious, fellonious, and moſt impudent actings, and Gods mercy in our preſervation. The people being all well ſatisfied, I ſent for the priſoners one by one before</hi> the united authority <hi>of the Colony; where their</hi> charges
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105536:14"/>and impeachments <hi>were read, evidence</hi> viva voce <hi>of the words and actions; which the annexed depoſitions will at large declare. And according to their</hi> crimes and qualities <hi>were cenſured, ſome to depart the Colony, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in five years, others to depart and were fined, others were fined and not ſent off: but one as deep as the reſt carrying himſelf with remorſe ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and civility, obtained a more moderate cenſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect,</hi> 15. There is a ſort of men in the world that will <hi>ſay</hi> more in their friends behalf then they will <hi>ſwear, and ſuch Byam</hi> hath got to prove the publiſhing of a <hi>Royal Proclamation,</hi> which I cannot hear any man in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſay <hi>he ever heard or ſaw.</hi> But it is ſomewhat ſtrange that <hi>Byam</hi> and <hi>Marten</hi> ſhould, not above a year before, themſelves form and contrive an <hi>Act</hi> for the <hi>General Aſſembly to paſs,</hi> wherein it was ordained, <hi>That the conſtitution of the Delegates ſhould not be altered though a Commiſſion came from the ſovereign power for the government or propriety, untill we had firſt ſent home to acquaint the power with the inconveniencies of admitting a change of rule, and obtained an anſwer;</hi> And that now upon a <hi>hear-ſay</hi> (nay ſome moneths before that <hi>hear-ſay</hi> arrived) they ſhould be the leading men to change <hi>this establiſhed form.</hi> But every man is neareſt to himſelf; and <hi>Marten,</hi> beſides, is ſo famous in <hi>nothing</hi> as his <hi>variety of councels:</hi> and it ſeems the <hi>whole bulk of Government</hi> muſt dance to the <hi>changes</hi> of his brain.</p>
               <p>Yet, how ſlender ſoever <hi>this proof</hi> was of a <hi>thing of that nature,</hi> it was ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent (and <hi>leſs</hi> would have <hi>been ſo</hi> in a matter that <hi>Byam would</hi> that it <hi>ſhould be</hi>) to cauſe <hi>this General Aſſembly</hi> (as they call themſelves) even before any of us were called before them, to <hi>ſentence the diſputes to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as a trayterous and rebellious oppoſing his Majeſties power, and the taking the Shallop</hi> (without ever examining any reaſons) <hi>as a felonious act:</hi> ſo that when we were brought to the <hi>Tribunal,</hi> it was to <hi>judgement,</hi> not to <hi>tryal,</hi> and accordingly we no ſooner appeared than received their condemnation.</p>
               <p>Now, though (be it true that <hi>theſe men</hi> heard ſuch a <hi>Proclamation</hi>) <hi>I</hi> will not determine how far ſuch Royal Edicts exact <hi>their</hi> obedience within <hi>whoſe precincts</hi> they never came to be publiſhed; yet, <hi>this I</hi> dare aver, <hi>that there was never any command from his Majeſty that any free-man ſhould be taken, diſſeized, and axiled without tryal by his Peers and the Law.</hi> Nor did the <hi>King</hi> authorize any to be <hi>Judges in their own cauſe;</hi> or ever grant <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to <hi>Byam</hi> to proceed againſt his Majeſties ſubjects by <hi>a martial court and way, contrary to the laws and franchiſes of the land:</hi> And yet ſee here <hi>Byams</hi> confeſſion for <hi>thus</hi> proceeding againſt us. Nor can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105536:15"/>they deny <hi>this</hi> by ſtiling themſelves <hi>the united authority;</hi> for grant their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <hi>lawfull,</hi> it cannot deprive us of our <hi>Magna Charta Priviledges.</hi> Let <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> declaim with a <hi>voice of thunder, and face of braſs</hi> that his Court is founded <hi>on the higheſt authority,</hi> yet nothing but an <hi>army</hi> can draw an <hi>honeſt mans ſilent aſsent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> cannot leſs wonder at the <hi>diverſities of judgements</hi> on one and the ſame fact; had the <hi>law</hi> appointed the <hi>penalty</hi> it could not have been <hi>ſo ſtrangely different,</hi> nor the <hi>Judge</hi> (if ſworn to obſerve <hi>that law</hi>) have dared to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe it in a <hi>various manner.</hi> Hence it is evident, their <hi>judgement,</hi> if by <hi>law,</hi> was by <hi>a diverſe and uncertain law,</hi> and, <hi>ubi lex aut vaga aut incerta mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerrima est ſervitus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 16. <hi>The laſt that came before authority was</hi> Lieutenant Collonel Sanford, <hi>who, though he brought up the</hi> Rear <hi>was the</hi> head of the faction. <hi>The first word that proceeded out of his mouth was</hi> the lye, <hi>which he ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with moſt impudent railing againſt the</hi> General Aſſembly: <hi>whereupon I remanded him to priſon to be ſecured in irons, and afterwards fined in five thouſand pounds of ſugar, and to be ſent off in the firſt ſhip bound for</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>which was his deſire.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. It is accompted a dangerous birth where the feet come formoſt, and certainly, if <hi>I</hi> were the <hi>head</hi> of this <hi>ſedition</hi> (as they call it) the chief reaſon of <hi>its miſcarriage</hi> was my appearing <hi>laſt</hi> in the action.</p>
               <p>The firſt word that proceeded out of my mouth was a <hi>truth,</hi> and that <hi>I</hi> ſeconded by <hi>others</hi> as <hi>great truths:</hi> but when my <hi>arguments grew of force I</hi> was ſilenced. And though <hi>this General Anſwer</hi> might ſerve well enough to <hi>his general criminations</hi> (ſuch kinde of <hi>Returns</hi> having been often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged <hi>iuſufficient,</hi> it being a Rule that <hi>Generale nil certi implicat;</hi> and therefore the law requires and injoyns <hi>certainty</hi>) yet <hi>I</hi> will be <hi>more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> (a curioſity which <hi>Byam</hi> hath no good ſucceſſe in, and therefore cunningly declines it) and tell the world the whole manner of my tryall.</p>
               <p>Being guarded up to the judgement-ſeat in the night through lanes of ſouldiers, <hi>Byam</hi> reads to me ſome depoſitions containing the manner of my attempting a <hi>reſcous</hi> on the priſoners: the witneſſes had not <hi>front enough</hi> to appear; and therefore <hi>I</hi> muſt credit <hi>Byam</hi> (though no ſworn Magiſtrate, and my enemy) that <hi>they had made ſuch oath.</hi> When he came to thoſe words, that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay to the priſoners <hi>[I will aſſiſt you with my life and fortunes] I</hi> ſaid, <hi>that was a lye whoever ſwore it.</hi> And ſo it was, for <hi>I</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid ſo; nor need <hi>I</hi> diſown it if <hi>I</hi> had ſpoke it, it being no crime for me
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105536:15"/>to declare a readineſſe of expoſing life and fortunes for the protection of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence from a violent oppreſſion. But to proceed; <hi>A ſilence</hi> expecting it, <hi>I</hi> ſpake theſe <hi>very and onely</hi> words. <hi>I</hi> ſee here ſo few formalities of a legal Court, that <hi>I</hi> ſhall uſe as few in confeſſing or denying what <hi>I</hi> ſtand accuſed of: nor can <hi>I</hi> expect a very equal proceeding, finding <hi>thoſe</hi> ſit as my <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> who are my <hi>accuſers;</hi> whom it concerns as much <hi>that I be guilty,</hi> as it concerns me <hi>to be not guilty. You Sir</hi> (to <hi>Byam</hi>) <hi>and Major Noel</hi> there, arreſted me for <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> you ought to <hi>proſecute,</hi> not to <hi>judge</hi> me.</p>
               <p>Byam <hi>replies;</hi> We did not arreſt you for <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> but as a <hi>Traytor</hi> to his Majeſty; and it was for oppoſing the authority of the Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> rejoyned; <hi>I</hi> oppoſed no <hi>lawfull authority, I</hi> endeavoured indeed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade away <hi>an illegall force and the oppreſsions of violence.</hi> At which <hi>Byam</hi> in a fury commanded the Marſhal to take me away, and lay me aboard in irons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The turning from them I ſaid;</hi> This <hi>I</hi> expected; <hi>I</hi> ſee the formalities of Olivers <hi>High Court of injuſtice,</hi> but not of any <hi>legal Court:</hi> my accuſation is <hi>Treaſon,</hi> not tryable by the <hi>laws,</hi> but in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Byam <hi>repeated it;</hi> We did not accuſe you of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> but as a <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I then anſwered;</hi> How <hi>I</hi> can be a <hi>Traytour</hi> without a <hi>guilt of Treaſon</hi> is a riddle which <hi>I</hi> hope you will reſolve one day. And ſo was guarded away, <hi>Marten</hi> giving his vote to hang me up at the window. And <hi>theſe, Reader,</hi> are the <hi>impudent railings</hi> for which <hi>this ſtrange ſentence</hi> paſſed on me; which <hi>I</hi> received not till about ten dayes after by the hands of the <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that it may yet more clearly appear it was <hi>private animoſities,</hi> not any <hi>deſigns of ours againſt the Countrey,</hi> that drew on this puniſhment; <hi>Marten</hi> about this time was heard to ſay [<hi>Had</hi> Sparrow <hi>and</hi> Harmund <hi>been now alive, they muſt have gone the ſame way: but, God be thanked, the Countrey is now pretty well purged from them all one way or other.</hi>] Theſe two were dead before there was any occaſion for the preſent diſputes; and than whom none could be more induſtrious or ſucceſſefull in their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. They had indeed frequent conteſts with <hi>Byam</hi> and <hi>Marten,</hi> being too much Engliſh men to be enſlaved or abuſed. Nor was this puniſhment of <hi>baniſhing</hi> any other then <hi>Marten's invention,</hi> which <hi>his Ecch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Knightly</hi> long before in a <hi>drunken liberality</hi> diſcovered.</p>
               <p>But <hi>I</hi> wonder to hear <hi>Byam</hi> ſay <hi>it was my deſire</hi> to be ſent for <hi>England,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> accounted one of the cleareſt evidences that themſelves were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of their injuſtice, and therefore removed me from all aſſiſtance for <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair:</hi> the <hi>Reader, I</hi> think, can finde no <hi>ſuch deſire</hi> in my words, not muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105536:16"/>my <hi>judges</hi> perſwade me that they ſtudied <hi>my pleaſure</hi> in my <hi>pain. Marten</hi> was more ingenuous when he ſaid, <hi>[ſend him for England, and let him be put aſhore on the firſt land, and then let him prate, every petty fogger there will ſilence him.]</hi> They knew very well that I had not been out of the <hi>Indies</hi> from my childhood, in near twenty years: if they would indeed have conformed to <hi>law</hi> and my <hi>deſire,</hi> they ſhould have ſent me to <hi>England</hi> to be tryed for the <hi>treaſon</hi> they charged me with: and then I ſhould have had hopes in time to have found <hi>them here to proſecute me.</hi> Nor can I yet underſtand how they will anſwer the accuſing us of <hi>felony, treaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and enmity to the King,</hi> and prove nothing of <hi>this</hi> againſt us. Slander is one kinde of treſpaſs, and the law gives action for it: and theſe criminations which they have deviſed againſt us, if falſe, are ſlanders of the blackeſt mouth, and may poſſibly be found meritorious of the <hi>Penalties of Conſpiracy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 17 <hi>If I ſhould adde ſome circumſtances of theſe paſſages, and the carriages of theſe incorrigible men before Authority, it would hugely ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate their crimes: but they are ſufficiently ſullyed by what hath been ſaid already without caſting more dirt in their faces.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 17 Should I aggravate every expreſſion and uſage of theſe unjuſt and malitious proſcuters: and expatiate into that large diſcourſe how, not content with what they had already made us ſuffer, they purſued us with avarice as well as malice, endeavouring to ſeize to themſelues the poore remains of our ſhattered fortunes; which, how contemptible ſoever, it ſeems they thought them worth the having; ſhould I doe this, I ſay, it would caſt ſo much black upon them as would blot out quite <hi>the complexion of Chriſtians.</hi> But their own Declaration, diſcovering ſo little of crime, and ſuch huge inflictions and penalties, and yet (as though innocency were not enough ſtained by their actions) aſperſing us with ſuch hideous calumnies as reach to the depriving us of our humane eternity, in blaſting the fame of our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, this very Declaration preſents them <hi>fallen from humanity;</hi> and ſhews, how confident they are that the <hi>blow</hi> they have given us was <hi>home,</hi> and we never likely to recover our feet; and therefore they may the more freely trample us in in the dirt and take the pleaſure of the <hi>tongue</hi> as they have of the <hi>hand</hi> already. But a time may come when this very <hi>Libel</hi> of theirs, will be enough to charge them to <hi>their ruine,</hi> thought not to <hi>our reſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="declaration">
               <head>Declaration.</head>
               <p>Sect. 18. Neceſſity <hi>and</hi> conveniency <hi>enforced to this mannerr of</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105536:16"/>
                  <hi>againſt theſe Delinquents; in which our</hi> moderation <hi>may, I am ſure our</hi> ſeverity <hi>cannot be taxed. I have expoſed this Paper to the</hi> view, <hi>and I hope to the</hi> ſatisfaction of the inquiſitive: <hi>and doe</hi> ſeriouſly atteſt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereof by my ſubſcription.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Will. Byam <hi>Governour.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. The law indeed favours ſome actions, when for the doing of them there is <hi>neceſſity</hi> or <hi>conveniency;</hi> but if a <hi>thief</hi> plead <hi>either</hi> in excuſe of his felony, it will be well examined <hi>how great,</hi> and <hi>how alowable it is.</hi> And ſhould theſe actions come to <hi>ſuch a test,</hi> I durſt be again the <hi>Butt</hi> for <hi>Byams</hi> malice, if any the leaſt <hi>lawful neceſſity</hi> or <hi>conveniency</hi> would appear for <hi>theſe proceedings.</hi> However, I am glad I have his hand to <hi>attest</hi> this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and onely wiſh I had occaſion to try whether he would be Gent. enough not to retract <hi>this ſerious averment nor deny this ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I</hi> will promiſe him not to charge more to him then he here confeſſeth himſelf guilty of, if he will but admit <hi>this</hi> as an evidence. But though, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, he thinks that he now playes ſecurely, having put us out of all ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal poſſibility of bringing him to an after game, yet will <hi>I</hi> not ſin ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the dignity of Juſtice as to deſpair her taking cognizance of my caſe; and then <hi>I</hi> fear not, but that <hi>this Declaration of Byams</hi> may diſpoſe her to a retribution: my <hi>poverty I</hi> hope will <hi>ſpeed,</hi> not <hi>retard</hi> her repair, and what hath <hi>ſhortned</hi> my hands will <hi>lenghten hers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince the Gentleman is ſo confident that he hath not dealt over-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely with us, <hi>I</hi> onely wiſh he may finde <hi>an equal mercy and moderation</hi> when ever he hath occaſion; and then, poſſibly, he may begin to weigh what it is to be baniſhed from eſtate and relations, to be put out of a ſettled and comfortable way of being, and expoſed to the contempt of beggery and deration of a wife and children partners in the ſufferance: and <hi>all this</hi> for actions rather <hi>honest</hi> then <hi>criminal.</hi> The divine retaliation deal to <hi>Byam and his aſſeſſors</hi> as they have dealt to <hi>me,</hi> and no better to me then <hi>I</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from that Colony, and them; <hi>I</hi> think the world will judge, <hi>I need not beg a curſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Come we now to the Teſtimonies which were brought againſt us, and the particular facts of which we are charged, as they are by <hi>Byam</hi> himſelf expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the worlds view: But before <hi>I</hi> come to <hi>their</hi> examination <hi>I</hi> ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe a few things to the <hi>readers</hi> conſideration.</p>
               <p>There is not, in my opinion, a more rational evidence of the ſlenderneſs of our guilt then our <hi>charge,</hi> if we conſider the <hi>inquiſition</hi> upon our actions; which was managed in our abſence by the ſubtileſt of our enemies, and principal parties concerned in the quarrel; who having already deſigned
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105536:17"/>us for deſtruction, and acted againſtus with conformable injuries, had a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> urging them to make us as criminal as was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Byam therefore,</hi> when he had ſeized &amp; impriſoned our perſons, ſends for all that can pretend to know or to have heard any thing that might render us culpable, and takes their <hi>Depoſitions:</hi> the <hi>reader</hi> may finde by the dates of moſt of them that they were <hi>taken</hi> before our time of trial, while we were cooped up, ignorant of our crime and accuſer: <hi>their contents</hi> will ſhew that much of our offence is <hi>words;</hi> and let <hi>candor</hi> determine, whether the moſt innocent perſons may not be deſtroyed (where <hi>words</hi> are <hi>capital</hi>) if <hi>his enemy,</hi> who is <hi>concerned in his ruine,</hi> have the ſole examination of ſuch men as <hi>himſelf</hi> will call for, and makes ſevere ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny into all his diſcourſes; picking there-hence <hi>ſuch words</hi> as may ſerve his malicious purpoſe, and cunningly omitting <hi>thoſe, which,</hi> being ſpoken at the ſame time, might <hi>extenuate,</hi> if not <hi>amove,</hi> the evil of <hi>the other:</hi> inſerting neither the <hi>occaſion, incitements, time, place,</hi> nor <hi>condition of the ſpeaker; circumſtances</hi> which illuſtrate a diſcourſe, and make it often appear very divers from the ſenſe of ſome of its words. Nor will his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> let us expect more <hi>integrity</hi> in <hi>Byam,</hi> ſince when the <hi>reader</hi> hath throughly read and weighed him, he will all along finde him <hi>ſtretching his criminations</hi> beyond any thing of <hi>proof</hi> which he could purchaſe againſt us. <hi>And that ſtrange paſsage of Harmunds and Lacons</hi> (ſome years before) <hi>whoſe names</hi> (vvritten in their ovvn character) <hi>were found as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to a bill of debt due to Byam, and yet themſelves did upon their oaths declare they never ſaw that deed before, nor were in place when it was made,</hi> makes me ready to conclude <hi>him not very ſcrupulous of anothers perjury where it may be to his advantage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though <hi>Byam</hi> aſſert that <hi>evidence was given vivâ voce</hi> of our <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions,</hi> yet <hi>I</hi> ſhall deſire the reader to underſtand him rightly vvhat he meanes by <hi>vivâvoce;</hi> it vvas not that the vvitneſs came in, in preſence of the priſoner, and there, upon <hi>a mutual confrontment,</hi> did take his oath, and then, <hi>upon that oath,</hi> charge the priſoner vvith ſuch and ſuch facts, the priſoner having liberty of <hi>putting queſtions</hi> to him, and <hi>the court of his ſide</hi> to enjoin an anſvver to <hi>ſuch queſtions:</hi> but, as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before, all or moſt of the vvitneſſes vvere ſvvore before-hand in the priſoners abſence, <hi>Byam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the man that took the Depoſitions, as much (<hi>I</hi> muſt ſuppoſe) to our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage as he could: and then vvhen the Delinquents vvere brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, <hi>this Depoſition</hi> vvas read in preſence of the <hi>witneſs,</hi> vvho <hi>by his ſilence</hi> aſſerts it; and if the priſoner began to <hi>queſtion him, Marten and Noel</hi> vvould call it impudence to argue againſt an oath, and <hi>Byam</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Marſhal to take him avvay and lay him in irons.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105536:17"/>
               <p>Nor had every one priviledge of <hi>ſeeing his accuſer,</hi> but vvas condemned on <hi>Depoſitions</hi> taken God knovvs <hi>when, where</hi> or <hi>of whom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet all this notvvithſtanding, they found (as <hi>I</hi> hope the <hi>reader</hi> alſo vvill) our faults ſo much beneath the puniſhment they had deſtinied us to, that they durſt not bring us before an <hi>indifferent Judicature, to a trial by our Peers,</hi> vvhere vve might have liberty of <hi>defending our actions by law,</hi> and ſhould have had <hi>our judges of councel with us, and ſworne to give judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to law;</hi> but brought us <hi>before themſelves</hi> (vvho vvere none of them ſvvorne Magiſtrates except thoſe tvvo that vvere my aſſiſtants in the court of Common-pleas) where we were not permitted to enter on any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (<hi>that</hi> being preſently adjudged as an aggravation of our guilt) but, according to their own wills and prejudices, ſentenced to inflictions not to be precedented, I think, in the <hi>whole body</hi> of our <hi>law, Statute</hi> or <hi>Common.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And herein they acted not onely <hi>Counter to the lawes of England</hi> (to which they had alwaies owned a ſubjection) but to <hi>their own conſtitutions</hi> alſo (one inſtance of <hi>that ſubjection:</hi>) for, not many moneths before, theſe very men Enacted <hi>[That a General Seſſions of the Peace and Goal delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be held twice a year,</hi> viz. <hi>On the first thurſday in September, and the first thurſday in March. That this General Seſſions doe by a Jury of Grand Inquest enquire into all breaches of the Peace, and breaches of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and all criminal matters whatſoever, and make preſentment thereof by Indictment: and proceed to the puniſhment of all malefactours, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where it concernes life or limb, according to the known lawes of England.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>this</hi> was made while their authority was derived from the Delegates; they decreed then like <hi>Subſtitutes conforming to their Commiſſion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions;</hi> but ſince <hi>that</hi> they have given <hi>themſelves a greater latitude of Power, a Power not differing from abſoluteneſs; which</hi> that they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with the leſs controll, they muſt remove <hi>them who</hi> have been ſo long the obſtacles to it: and becauſe <hi>ſuch a general ſeſſions as this Act preſcribes</hi> cannot compleat <hi>their deſires,</hi> therefore are they <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to this <hi>other manner of proceedings.</hi> But God grant us more indifferent judges of <hi>this neceſſity</hi> then perſons <hi>ſo deeply intereſſed;</hi> who having themſelves <hi>created it</hi> by uſurping a power over <hi>us,</hi> could no other way ſecure themſelves (in the <hi>diſpute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> made to their power</hi>) from a being <hi>cast in their own action,</hi> but by an <hi>illegal proſecution of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I will no longer detein the <hi>Reader from a view of the Depoſitions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of Capt.</hi> Tho. Griffith <hi>aged forty years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts taken before me this</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661.</head>
               <p>1. Saith. <hi>That ſometime in July last or thereabouts, being at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105536:18"/>houſe of</hi> Mr. Michael Maſhart, <hi>and having ſome diſcourſe of what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the last Aſſembly,</hi> the Deponent <hi>told him that it was ordered that the Governour ſhould continue and no new Election to be, and this by vertue of a</hi> Proclamation <hi>from the</hi> King.</p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Sworne before me</hi> 
                  <signed>William Byam.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Themſelves have confeſſed that the <hi>Kings Proclamation</hi> never came to be publiſhed amongſt us (and indeed how ſhould it ſince <hi>ſuch Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> never was?) and alſo that <hi>this very order</hi> for their Authorities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation was never <hi>proclaimed,</hi> but onely <hi>mentioned</hi> by ſome few Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Aſſembly <hi>in their occaſional diſcourſes;</hi> as is confeſſed here and in <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Yet ſee how ſeverely they puniſh <hi>the breach of a law which never had promulgation.</hi> But grant <hi>this order duly publiſhed,</hi> the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtill is, <hi>whether the power conſtituted can alter the Decree of the Power conſtituting in that very point wherein themſelves were reſtrained; ſince it is an Aphoriſme in law and reaſon that unumquodque diſſolvitur eodem modo quo colligatum est?</hi> We will confeſſe that by the <hi>implyed ſanction</hi> of thoſe Delegates <hi>the Soveraign of our nation could reſcind their dictates;</hi> but our enemies alſo confeſs (in accuſing us of it) that we conſtantly denyed the iſſuing forth <hi>of any ſuch ſoveraign command;</hi> nor can they charge us <hi>with any proof of their contrary affirmation:</hi> for I will not be ſo uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to this Gentleman Deponent as to think he ſwears <hi>[This order was by vertue of the Kings Proclamation]</hi> but that he onely ſwears <hi>[he told Mr. Maſhart it was ſo]</hi> and whether <hi>Mr. Maſhart</hi> was bound to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</hi> him, and did ſuffer juſtly <hi>for his incredulity,</hi> I leave to <hi>their deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> who know <hi>there was never any ſuch Proclamation from His Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of Mr.</hi> Francis Sanford <hi>aged thirty one years or thereabouts, taken before me this</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661.</head>
               <p>2. Saith. <hi>That being at</hi> Patham hill <hi>in company with Mr.</hi> Michael Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhart <hi>the Deponent heard him ſay, that he did not own the Governour as Governour, nor any thing the General Aſſembly did, for he owned no Power in the Colony as yet. And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne before me <signed>Will. Byam.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Reader</hi> hath heard that <hi>Byam, and that ſame General Aſſembly</hi> now ruling with him, were appointed by <hi>Delegates</hi> impowred by the People to erect <hi>a frame of Government;</hi> that they were limited to rule but one year; that they continued themſelves by no greater real power then their own. Whether <hi>Maſhart</hi> therefore were criminal in ſaying as he did, or whether <hi>this Governour and General Aſſembly</hi> (who trembled at the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105536:18"/>thought of being turned out) were likely to be <hi>equal judges of this diſpute, or the perſon that made them, I</hi> leave to the <hi>leſs partial reader.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Sergeant Major George Uſher <hi>aged fifty two years or thereabouts taken before me this</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661.</head>
               <p>Saith. <hi>That being ſent from the Governour to</hi> M. Maſhart <hi>to require him</hi> in his Majeſties name <hi>to appear before him;</hi> to whom <hi>the ſaid</hi> Maſhart <hi>replyed, that he knew no Governour, nor would obey any till a new Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, neither Councel nor Aſſembly. And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sworne before me <hi>W. B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="3">3. This is ſo like <hi>the former</hi> that the ſame anſwer may ſerve to it; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Deponent</hi> might have added, that <hi>Mr. Maſhart</hi> ſaid <hi>[he owned His Majeſty, but knew no Governour]</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Edward Dod <hi>aged thirty nine years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts taken before me this</hi> 29<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661.</head>
               <p n="4">4. Saith. <hi>That meeting Mr</hi> Daniel Jones <hi>upon the river by</hi> Mr. Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lys <hi>houſe, giving him the time of the day, and asking him how he did; he replyed, the worſe for ſuch rogues as thou art; and then, threatning him ſaid, I will draw up with ſuch rogues as thou art one after another: and further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne by me <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="4">4. When it was that <hi>this Deponent</hi> met with <hi>Jones,</hi> and received this churliſh return to his civil ſalute is not inſerted. But <hi>this Dod</hi> was a former adverſary to <hi>Jones,</hi> in the buſineſſe for which that unjuſt and malicious fine of five thouſand pounds of ſugar (before hinted at <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.) was impoſed: now probably <hi>Jones</hi> met <hi>this Antagoniſt</hi> ſoon after, while yet his choler boiled with the agitations of his ſoul on that ſharp injury, and was the more irritated in receiving a fawning treatment from a malicious proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. And ſince amongſt us in that Colony this phraſe of <hi>drawing up</hi> had its moſt common uſe, and that <hi>we there</hi> underſtood it <hi>in a great variety of ſenſes, good and bad;</hi> I ſuppoſe <hi>Jones</hi> ought to have been permitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to define <hi>in what manner he would draw up with Dod,</hi> perhaps he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned <hi>by benefits to draw on his repentance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The depoſition of</hi> Obadiah Gardiner, <hi>aged twenty two years, or thereabouts, taken before me this</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</head>
               <p n="5">5. Saith, <hi>That on the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> this moneth, <hi>being at Mr.</hi> Maſharts <hi>houſe he met with</hi> Daniel Jones <hi>with his naked rapier in his hand, and he asked the Deponent whether he knew that Mr.</hi> Michael Maſhart <hi>had any hand in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105536:19"/>taking the Shallop? to whom this Deponent replyed, I cannot tell, for I ſaw him at Collonel</hi> Ely's; <hi>to which</hi> Jones <hi>made anſwer, if that he did know that Mr.</hi> Maſhart <hi>were aboard the Shallop, he would go to him and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him in it. And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me. <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="5">5. To them that know not our <hi>Surinam dreſs,</hi> it may ſeem odd for a man to travel with his naked rapier; but let the <hi>Reader</hi> underſtand, that <hi>the going without a ſword</hi> was not more common; for thoſe that had been there many years, <hi>conſtant uſe</hi> had worn out their ſcabbards, and there were neither ſhops nor Artiſts to renew them: wherefore it was very uſual to ſtick ſomewhat upon the point of their rapier, to prevent a caſual injury to themſelves, or their aſſociates, and ſo to wear them either in their hands, or by their ſides.</p>
               <p>By the queſtions <hi>Jones</hi> made with <hi>this Deponent</hi> it ſhould ſeem he was ignorant whether Mr. <hi>Maſhart</hi> had any thing to do with ſeizing the Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop, and conſequently, it could not be a <hi>deſign</hi> of long contrivance, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ought againſt the Colony; for them me-thinks <hi>Jones</hi> (who was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered one of the firſt in plotting <hi>that countreys ruine</hi>) ſhould not now, <hi>in the execution of it,</hi> have been omitted. But how ſhall we underſtand theſe unadviſed ſpeeches of <hi>Jones,</hi> a ſingle man armed <hi>onely with a rapier?</hi> they are laid to be uttered the 25. of <hi>November:</hi> when <hi>Uſher</hi> had already recovered the Shallop, and <hi>Byam,</hi> with his guard of <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> taken her ſeizers, (as <hi>Sect.</hi> 12, 13.) <hi>The worſt</hi> that can be thought of it is, that, <hi>as in the former depoſition we finde</hi> Jones <hi>revengefull of an injury,</hi> ſo here <hi>he is the like of a benefit: Maſhart</hi> had endangered himſelf <hi>in his behalf,</hi> and now <hi>he</hi> would <hi>ſacrifice himſelf</hi> to evidence <hi>his gratitude:</hi> for other he could not hope in thruſting himſelf into the crouds of his armed enemies.</p>
               <p>I have a little inverted the order which <hi>Byam</hi> rangeth theſe depoſitions in; becauſe <hi>theſe two</hi> being lodged in one cenſure together, I would joyn <hi>their charge,</hi> that the <hi>Reader</hi> might the better take the <hi>parallel</hi> between their <hi>fact and puniſhment.</hi> Here then is <hi>their whole impeachment,</hi> both <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>form:</hi> (onely that we ſhall by and by finde Mr. <hi>Maſhart</hi> in the number of <hi>them that took the Shallop</hi>) and for <hi>this</hi> they received (as <hi>Byam</hi> ſtiles it) <hi>this moderate ſentence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By the Governour and General Aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ordered by the Authority aforeſaid, that Mr. <hi>Michael Maſhart,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Daniel Jones</hi> pay unto the <hi>publick</hi> five thouſand pounds of ſugar, and be ſecured in <hi>irons</hi> under a <hi>ſtrong guard,</hi> and be <hi>ſent off</hi> in the firſt ſhip that ſhall ſail hence for <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> and not return for five years after the date hereof, without his <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſpecial order: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105536:19"/>made ſufficiently evident that the ſaid <hi>Maſhart</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> have been and are, moſt <hi>ſeditious, rebellious, obſtinate</hi> and <hi>dangerous perſons</hi> to the Authority of <hi>this Colony.</hi> Dated 30. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 61.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Byam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whatever ſenſe may at firſt ſight ſeem in <hi>thoſe words relating to the fine,</hi> yet the Judges interpreted it to be <hi>five thouſand pounds of ſugar apiece,</hi> and accordingly exacted from their eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The depoſition of</hi> Henry Batſon, <hi>aged twenty four years, or thereabouts, taken before me this</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</head>
               <p n="6">6. Saith, <hi>That he heard Captain</hi> Thomas Crook <hi>ſay that within ſix moneths he would break this Colony, or elſe he would break his own neck:</hi> and further ſaid, <hi>That here were two men that would conduct them, one in the front, and the other in the rear to keep them forward. And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me, <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="deposition">
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The depoſition of Mr.</hi> Thomas Lewis ſenior, <hi>aged fifty years, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, taken before me this</hi> 28. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</head>
               <p n="7">7. Saith, <hi>that he heard Captain</hi> Crook <hi>ſay at</hi> Paramórabo <hi>on the</hi> 13. <hi>of</hi> November 1661. <hi>that he would break the neck of the Colony in ſix moneths, or elſe break his own neck: &amp; that if he were clapt up in priſon, he would have his way out the first ſhip that ſhould come in: and further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me, <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6, 7" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>6.7. The moſt material words in theſe depoſitions are thoſe which me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace the Colony: they are laid to be ſpoken the 13. of <hi>November,</hi> which was the time of my return from the <hi>Indian expedition;</hi> by the ſubſequent words in <hi>Lewis</hi>'s oath <hi>[about finding his way out of priſon]</hi> is proved that <hi>theſe diſcourſes</hi> were occaſioned <hi>from thoſe threats we receiveá at our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn:</hi> on <hi>which, Crook</hi> might poſſibly ſay, <hi>if theſe doings break not the Colony, I will break my neck,</hi> or to that effect, which the <hi>ſwearers</hi> or <hi>takers</hi> have wreſted to a worſe ſenſe. But admit he ſaid onely as <hi>they ſwear, and meant</hi> what he <hi>ſaid;</hi> Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgeman,</hi> in his <hi>excellent charge</hi> at the <hi>Old Baily;</hi> declareth, that in caſe of that <hi>prodigious treaſon of killing the King</hi> the Statute puniſheth the <hi>bare imagination,</hi> but in all other ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſaith he, our rule is, <hi>non officit con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>us niſi ſequetur effectus.</hi> And <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> diſcourſing upon <hi>this maxime,</hi> cites my Lord <hi>Coke</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>fol.</hi> 93. <hi>Bagges caſe</hi>) for <hi>this Law; Offices of truſt ſhall not be forfeited, nor pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in a Commonwealth loſt, by bare endeavours and intentions of doing acts contrary to that truſt, and in prejudice to that Commonwealth; no, though thoſe intents be publiſhed by evil threatning words, unleſs they be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105536:20"/>put in execution by ſome over-act.</hi> As to his endeavour of finding the way out of priſon, if he were put in, I think it is <hi>too natural</hi> to be condemned: And I remember to have read, that if a <hi>Sheriff</hi> by warrant of <hi>law</hi> onely <hi>(not of record)</hi> arreſt one for felony who is not guilty, he may <hi>reſcue</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. The <hi>words</hi> in <hi>Batſons</hi> oath, of <hi>[two men to conduct, &amp;c.]</hi> are <hi>too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> to prove any <hi>certain guilt:</hi> why might they not be ſpoken upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the preſent expedition we were juſt then returned from? <hi>Batſon,</hi> wondring that when the rumours were ſo loud of the <hi>Indians</hi> malice and power, we would, yet, venture ſo farre into <hi>their quarters</hi> and bring away <hi>ſo eminent an Indian priſoner through all their towns, being a party of but twenty men; Crook,</hi> in a ſlighting the <hi>Indians force</hi> and exalting <hi>ours,</hi> might ſay [<hi>there were two men</hi> &amp;c.] And indeed <hi>theſe words</hi> ſeem but <hi>part of a diſcourſe,</hi> which muſt have ſomewhat <hi>precedent</hi> or <hi>ſubſequent</hi> to illuſtrate it; and I may well ſuſpect that, <hi>though they would inſert nothing that might render the ſpeaker innocent,</hi> yet, <hi>they would not omit any thing that might make him guilty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> M. Tho. Stantor <hi>aged thirty two years or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts taken before me this</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661</head>
               <p n="8">8. Saith. <hi>That being at the</hi> Town <hi>when</hi> Lieutenant Col. Sanford <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned out of</hi> Camawyny, <hi>he heard</hi> Mr. Peter Fabian <hi>ſay, that they heard the Governour had cauſed Irons to be made for</hi> many of them <hi>against they came home, and</hi> ſome others <hi>which were in the Countrey;</hi> whom <hi>if</hi> they <hi>had found in priſon when they came home, they would fire the priſon and let them out: and ſaying</hi> ſomething <hi>about</hi> breaking the country, Captain Crook <hi>made anſwer</hi> [that is done already and I know who muſt enjoy it.] <hi>And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <hi>Sworne</hi> &amp;c. <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>This teſtimony</hi> clears <hi>that truth,</hi> that at our returne <hi>many were menaced with irons.</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>thereby</hi> exaſperated and urged to ſuch paſſionated di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſes as are here charged to them. Nor can I think (if any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration then <hi>the Governours want of Authority,</hi> and <hi>his uſurping on the peoples priviledges,</hi> had provoked them to theſe ranting expreſſions,) that the <hi>ſpeakers</hi> would have had ſo little moderation as thus publickly to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcover their <hi>immature deſigne</hi> before <hi>thoſe</hi> whom they knew <hi>the Governours ſpies;</hi> and <hi>at the ſame time</hi> put themſelves <hi>out of their armes, and better poſture of offence or defence;</hi> ſo farre am I from underſtanding <hi>theſe words</hi> as a leaſt circumſtance of <hi>any dark conſpiracy</hi> againſt the Colony. And as to the laſt point of the impeachment <hi>[his ſaying ſomething about break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the countrey]</hi> ſince the Deponent tells not <hi>what that ſomething was;</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105536:20"/>and ſince we may reaſonably enough conclude that <hi>had it been any thing ill it would have been Recorded,</hi> we may from <hi>Crookes</hi> anſwer affirm, that <hi>Fabian declaimed againſt theſe doings as tending to the Colonies breach;</hi> for it is known the Colony was not <hi>[already broke]</hi> but in theſe Gentlemens contemplations <hi>on the iſſue of theſe commotions:</hi> and hence alſo may the <hi>ſenſe and maner,</hi> in which <hi>Crooke denounced this breach,</hi> be illuſtrated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> David Bucket <hi>aged forty ſeaven years,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>The Deponent maketh oath that at the houſe of</hi> James Atkins and Thomas Stantor <hi>one night ſome weeks past, he heard</hi> Enſigne William San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>ſay that his warrant was as good as the Governours; upon which the Deponent made anſwer, how must we live? If a Commiſſion come from England from the</hi> King <hi>you must be all hanged: to which</hi> Enſigne Sanford <hi>ſaid, we will put that to a venture; and being further indiſcourſe he ſaid, the Governours two braſs guns ſhould not ſave him:</hi> Mr. Stephen Neal <hi>told</hi> Enſigne Sanford <hi>that he might queſtion</hi> his Brother <hi>by what power he ſate on the</hi> Bench; <hi>to which</hi> he <hi>made anſwer, you are a fool if you do not. The Deponent demanded of</hi> Enſigne Sanford, <hi>how we ſhould be governed or by what Law? to which the ſaid</hi> Sanford <hi>ſaid, that the Governour would call us and try us</hi> by a Council of War <hi>for our lives and eſtates, and he would be hanged if there were any other: and further the Deponent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne before me <dateline>
                     <date>the 26<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of Novemb. 1661.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="9">9. This was the evening of <hi>that day</hi> in which my <hi>Brother</hi> had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the Governours power at <hi>Toorárica convention;</hi> (<hi>Sect.</hi> 5.) retiring thence into a Tavern, <hi>this Deponent</hi> and ſome others urged him upon <hi>that point;</hi> and he being young and hot ſpirited retorted according to their urgings, as ſhaming to recede from his own publick aſſertion. But he had the pardon of his judges and therefore needs the leſs of my labour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> James Atkins, <hi>aged thirty five years, or thereabouts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>The Deponent maketh oath, that about the latter end of</hi> October <hi>at night aſſembled together at his houſe Captain</hi> George Straunge, <hi>Enſign</hi> William Sanford, <hi>Ma.</hi> Thomas Archer, <hi>and ſeveral others, at which time Enſign</hi> Sanford <hi>ſaid that the Governour had no power, and that</hi> his <hi>(mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own power) was as good as the Governours, and better too for ought he knew: and if Major</hi> Byam <hi>ſhould grant a warrant to his Marſhal, or any other officer under him, for</hi> him, <hi>he would carry a stillet to in his pocket to rip out his guts; and that he would never goe without one: then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing about</hi> Jones, <hi>they ſaid, that if he ſhould be kept priſoner, they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105536:21"/>would pull down the houſe about his ears: then</hi> David Bucket <hi>made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that then there was no law in the Countrey;</hi> William Sanford <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, a Turd for your Law:</hi> David Bucket <hi>ſaid, then we muſt go to</hi> club-law. <hi>Captain</hi> Straunge, <hi>Enſign</hi> Sanford, <hi>and</hi> Thomas Archer <hi>ſaid, it is</hi> that <hi>we would have.</hi> David Bucket <hi>made anſwer, that then they were best beat up their drums, and ſee how many they would have of</hi> their ſide, <hi>and how many of</hi> the other. <hi>Captain</hi> Straunge <hi>(as the Deponent best remembers) made anſwer, ſo they would if there were either drum or trumpet to be got.</hi> David Bucket <hi>replyed, if a Commiſſion come out of</hi> England, <hi>you would be all hanged every man of you; they made anſwer, we will put</hi> that <hi>to a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. And farther the Deponent ſaith, that amongſt the diſcourſe Enſign</hi> Sanford <hi>ſaid, he was as good a man as the</hi> King, <hi>the</hi> King <hi>was but a man, and ſo was</hi> he: <hi>and the Deponent further ſaith not</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me <dateline>
                     <date>the 26. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="deposition">
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Thomas Quintyn, <hi>aged thirty ſeven years, or thereabouts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>The Deponent maketh oath to the within-mentioned depoſition,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the buſineſs of <hi>Jones,</hi> and the laſt part concerning the words about the King: <hi>and further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me <dateline>
                     <date>the 27. of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1661.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10, 11" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>10, 11. The words of illeſt ſound in <hi>theſe,</hi> and <hi>the former,</hi> Depoſitions being charged to my <hi>Brother,</hi> I ſhall a little the more largely declare how he came to be cleared: <hi>Byam</hi> and <hi>Marten</hi> being wrought upon by the tears of a <hi>Jew,</hi> who had great prevalencies on them, and as great affections for my <hi>Brother,</hi> they were reſolved not to urge any thing againſt him but <hi>thoſe words concerning the King:</hi> in <hi>which</hi> alſo they purpoſed to allow him all liberty to clear himſelf, if poſſible: being therefore called before them, the firſt evidence he brought for himſelf was the conſtant loyalty, which, to the knowledge of his Judges, he had expreſſed towards <hi>his Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> even in <hi>ſuch times</hi> as it was dangerous <hi>to own affection or eſteem:</hi> 2. <hi>Quintyn</hi> upon his oath had declared, that he knew nothing of <hi>theſe words</hi> though in the ſame ſociety: nay more, he had <hi>owned</hi> to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that <hi>himſelf</hi> ſpoke what was ſaid of the <hi>King</hi> (though far <hi>from a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing of Majeſty</hi>) and that he received <hi>a check</hi> from my Brother <hi>for na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the King at ſuch a time and place.</hi> 3. Mr. <hi>Neal</hi> was ready to aver the ſame: a rational perſon, and <hi>who at that time</hi> had mixed in much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſcourſe with my Brother. <hi>Theſe negatives</hi> ſatisfied the <hi>Judges,</hi> and my Brother was diſcharged on no other conditions <hi>than not to come near me, nor any of the priſoners.</hi> And that it may appear how little theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105536:21"/>did deſign <hi>a forceable maintaining their diſputes,</hi> I ſhall trouble the <hi>Reader</hi> with a letter which my Brother ſent to me <hi>upon occaſion of theſe words,</hi> when he yet expected not ſo ſudden an impriſonment: <hi>Byam</hi> hath ſeen it, and may remember <hi>the contents.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Letter.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brother, I am informed that divers ſtrange relations are vented abroad concerning me, whereby I am charged by ſome of</hi> Treaſon, <hi>by others of</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, <hi>and by thoſe that are moſt favourable, of</hi> backing a horrid faction and damnable deſign; <hi>amongſt whom I underſtand that</hi> David Bucket <hi>hath taken a depoſition againſt me, and</hi> (by malice ſuborned) <hi>declares that I did at the laſt publick meeting in a ſlighting manner ſay,</hi> the King is but a man, and ſo am I.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>None, beſides him, then preſent are ſenſible of any ſuch thing ſpoken; I remember</hi> that night <hi>as we were drinking,</hi> Bucket <hi>in ſome diſcourſe, but far from that ſubject, gave me</hi> the lye; <hi>whereupon I offered to ſtrike him, but was hindred by Mr.</hi> Neal; <hi>yet ſo much threatened him, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the company, and hath ſince broacht his forgery.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I ſhall requeſt you on</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">This vvas the day for the Countries meeting. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</note> 
                        <hi>Thurſday next to bring with you what</hi> Books, <hi>or the like, that may be made uſe of in the queſtion of</hi> Treaſon; <hi>for I then expect the</hi> whole power <hi>of the Governour to be directed againſt thoſe</hi> who have thwarted his deſires: <hi>and I know his</hi> hatred to be as endleſs as his ambition is boundleſs.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>I am <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>This</hi> came to my hands the 22, of <hi>November,</hi> the day before the Shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop was taken; when I was arreſted it was in my pocket: <hi>which,</hi> by <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> commands, being ſearched, <hi>this</hi> was taken out and carried to him; who peruſed it and returned it to me again.</p>
               <p>But how well ſoever my Brother ſcaped, <hi>this depoſition</hi> muſt retain its force againſt Captain <hi>Straunge,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Archer,</hi> to whom <hi>thoſe words, they would have club-law,</hi> and, <hi>if there were either drums or trumpets to be got they would ſound them,</hi> were reckoned with all poſſible aggravations; <hi>which,</hi> that they might not looſe <hi>their weight,</hi> the priſoners are hurried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to irons aſſoon as they appear, <hi>before they can open in a defence:</hi> who elſe had <hi>this</hi> to plead for themſelves: <hi>Lubricum linguae non facile in poenam eſt trahendum; this</hi> was <hi>Tavern-diſcourſe</hi> into which they were <hi>quareled,</hi> and <hi>urged by reflections on their lost priviledges:</hi> at worſt, they were but <hi>evidences of their evil intents,</hi> of <hi>which</hi> it was a great argument <hi>that they had repented,</hi> in that, when <hi>ſo ſuddenly after</hi> they had <hi>arms</hi> put into their hands, and <hi>a good occaſion</hi> for ſucceſsfully <hi>beating up their drums</hi> (Sect. 7.) they employed <hi>both</hi> in the Countries <hi>ſervice, honour,</hi> and <hi>ſecurity.</hi> Beſides,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105536:22"/>to them that know that the Colony had neither <hi>drum nor trumpet</hi> in it, <hi>that expreſſion</hi> may rather ſeem a <hi>ſcoff</hi> than a <hi>threat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince <hi>Byam</hi> here takes ſuch <hi>ſtrict accompts of words,</hi> we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him how he hath heard <hi>the Saviour of the world worſe than blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, his enemies the</hi> Jews <hi>crying ſhame at the fact and connivance;</hi> and how <hi>himſelf hath laboured the Judge</hi> (even while <hi>himſelf was Governour</hi>) <hi>to pronounce a remiſſion: giving ſuch publick countenance to the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer as his very adorer</hi> Uſher <hi>condemned:</hi> And how frequently he hath been delighted with <hi>Martens witty prophanations of the ſacred Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, atheistically, with ſcoffs, controverting all its moſt reverend, most univerſally embraced, and most comfortable</hi> Credenda; <hi>ſeldome ſparing his God in his jeſt.</hi> Since he is now become <hi>ſo ſevere a puniſher of words</hi> (and <hi>of words, whoſe horridity</hi> (to uſe <hi>his own phraſe</hi>) <hi>is infinitely inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to thoſe</hi> which moved him <hi>leſs</hi>) let him be <hi>ſo ingenuous</hi> as to let <hi>his own mouth</hi> as well condemn him of <hi>partiality,</hi> as my <hi>very charity</hi> perſwades me <hi>his conſcience does.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Thomas Duke, <hi>aged twenty ſix years, or thereabouts, taken before me the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</head>
               <p n="12">12. Saith, <hi>That on Saturday laſt being the</hi> 22. <hi>of this inſtant, about ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the</hi> clock, <hi>there came aboard</hi> Cryn Jacobſons <hi>Shallop</hi> (<hi>then at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor above</hi> Morganàm) <hi>Captain</hi> George Straunge, <hi>Captain</hi> Thomas Crook, <hi>Mr.</hi> Michael Maſhart, <hi>Mr.</hi> Anthony Wroth, <hi>Mr.</hi> Peter Wroth, <hi>Mr.</hi> Rowland Bulkly, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Thomas Archer, <hi>and told the ſeamen</hi> (whereof the Deponent was one) <hi>that they ſeized the Shallop for his Majeſties ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and forced the ſeamen to go aſhore, haling and abuſing them.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="deposition">
               <p>13 Jacob Reyner <hi>aged twenty five years, and</hi> Alexander O-Bryan, <hi>aged twenty years or thereabouts,</hi> depoſeth the ſame <hi>before me.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Thomas Duke, <hi>aged twenty ſix years, or thereabouts, taken before me this</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> November. 1661.</head>
               <p n="14">14. Saith, <hi>That two of his mates,</hi> Jacob Reyner, <hi>and</hi> Alexander O-Bryan <hi>were turned aſhore, and that</hi> he the Deponent <hi>was detained aboard to wait on Captain</hi> Crook <hi>and his officers, and that firſt Mr.</hi> Anthony Wroth <hi>went into</hi> Cryns <hi>cabin, and took his ſmall box wherein his accounts and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers were, and peruſed them; then Captain</hi> Crook <hi>went into the</hi> hold, <hi>and opened</hi> Cryns <hi>cheſt, and</hi> Jacob Reyners, <hi>and took out all their clothes, hats, ſhoes, and divided them amongſt his company, and put a pair of the ſhoes on his feet, ſwearing grievouſly that they ſhould not take the ſhoes from his feet, but they ſhould take his life alſo: and that in the night there came
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105536:22"/>Captain</hi> Straunges Negroes, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Fabians <hi>with four fixed guns, and about ſeven pounds of powder: then came Mr.</hi> Needham <hi>with a launce and a piſtol; Captain</hi> Straunge, <hi>Mr.</hi> Fabian, <hi>Mr.</hi> William Sanford <hi>armed: but before that Captain</hi> Crook <hi>went about any thing, he took the Deponent, and clapt his hands behinde him (ſwearing horridly) that he would tye him, and burn his fingers with matches if he would not confeſs where the powder lay, and then with a light match burned him twice on the breaſt, threatning him. When the arms came aboard they charged three,</hi> beſides what was charged before, <hi>and being ready,</hi> Crook <hi>ſaid,</hi> now I wiſh the Governour would come to ſpeak with us. <hi>Further</hi> Crook <hi>ſaid,</hi> as for my part of this prize I value it not a pipe of Tobacco, it is another buſineſſe we are come about concerning the Countrey, about chuſing a new Governour. <hi>Further the ſaid</hi> Crook <hi>told them he would ſtop all boats, and ſpeak with them, and know their buſineſs; and</hi> on Munday following he would go to <hi>Toorárica,</hi> and ſtay till Thurſday to ſee whether the General Aſſembly would make her a prize; <hi>if not, he was reſolved to carry her to</hi> Barbadoes, <hi>thence to</hi> Jamai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, <hi>till he found</hi> the Kings Commiſſion <hi>to make her a prize: further</hi> Crook <hi>ſaid, that neither</hi> Dutch <hi>nor</hi> Jew <hi>ſhould live here. Further the</hi> Deponent <hi>ſaith, that Captain</hi> Crook <hi>made theſe officers,</hi> himſelf <hi>chief Captain, Mr.</hi> Thomas Archer <hi>his Lieutenant, Captain</hi> Straunge <hi>Maſter, Mr.</hi> Maſhart <hi>Boatſwain, Mr.</hi> William Needham <hi>his mate, Mr.</hi> Rowland Bulkely <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> Mr. Peter Wroth <hi>his mate, Mr.</hi> Peter Fabian <hi>Steward; and further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworn before me. <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12, 13, 14" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>12, 13, 14. Not content with <hi>that evidence</hi> which teſtified <hi>the whole ſubſtance of the fact</hi> of theſe men, <hi>the ſame Deponent</hi> is brought <hi>the ſecond time,</hi> to enlarge his oath <hi>with circumstances;</hi> It ſeems he did not ſwear <hi>the whole truth</hi> before, and, to mend that fault, <hi>now,</hi> I fear, hath ſworn <hi>more than the truth.</hi> And when the <hi>Reader</hi> conſiders <hi>this double ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> when he is told that the Deponent is a <hi>Dutchman, part-owner of the Shallop,</hi> who is to teſtifie againſt <hi>Engliſh men whom he hath already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to intend his ruine</hi> (not being made privy to their <hi>other ends</hi>) let him perpend how far <hi>revenge of an injury in one of a divers nation, and hopes of repair for that injury, meeting with a Judge who called for the worst that could be ſpoken, may operate against an abſent and already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned delinquent.</hi> But having been already very particular in the relation of ſeizing this Shallop, and <hi>the purpoſe</hi> of it (<hi>which</hi> is illuſtrated from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of <hi>theſe depoſitions</hi>) I ſhall onely trouble the <hi>Reader</hi> with a few things which I reſerved to this place. And firſt, <hi>that of opening the cheſt, and ſharing the clothes:</hi> had he had as much <hi>truth</hi> as <hi>malice,</hi> he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105536:23"/>ſo have ſworn that the clothes were all put up again, and nothing diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but an old clout given to an <hi>Indian,</hi> for which a <hi>treble return</hi> was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. I am ſure both <hi>Cryn</hi> and <hi>Reyner</hi> did acknowledge as much to me while I was a priſoner aboard them. 2. <hi>For the ſhoes;</hi> Captain <hi>Straunge,</hi> being to go to fetch ſome arms (a ſign they brought none with them) and wanting ſhoes <hi>(the then epidemic distreſs of the Colony)</hi> borrowed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain <hi>Crooks;</hi> and Captain <hi>Crook</hi> put on a pair which he found lying on the deck: <hi>of which</hi> he afterwards (upon ſurrender of the veſſel) acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Major <hi>Uſher,</hi> and had his leave to wear them up to Mr. <hi>Wroths,</hi> 3. <hi>To the tying and burning with match;</hi> Captain <hi>Crook</hi> had a cotton match in his hand to light his Tobacco (a ſort of match which takes fire and burns after the manner of tinder, and is therefore of neceſſary uſe for travellers in thoſe parts) one of the company asked <hi>this Deponent</hi> where the powder lay? he ſtanding ſilent, <hi>Crook</hi> flaps him in the face with this cotton match, and asketh him why he doth not ſpeak? And after when <hi>Crook</hi> at his tryal asked <hi>Duke</hi> (who ſtood to juſtifie his former oath) <hi>whether he opened his doublet to burn him on the breaſt, for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>you had a doublet on? Duke</hi> ſtood ſilent and non-pluſt: And <hi>that mark of burning</hi> which he ſhewed, was ſuch a ſpot as remains after a new-skin'd gall, and had no <hi>rawneſs</hi> nor <hi>looſe skin</hi> upon it or near it. But grant all this done in the very manner here mentioned; it was but a treſpaſſe, for which the <hi>parties grieved</hi> might have had <hi>their action,</hi> or at worſt <hi>an indictment, which</hi> they would hardly <hi>in equity,</hi> have been permitted to prove <hi>by their own oaths.</hi> The reſt of the things either <hi>make for us,</hi> and ſo are already inſtanced in, or elſe <hi>they are ridiculous.</hi> and ſo not worth the anſwering.</p>
               <p>And now the <hi>Reader</hi> hath the <hi>whole charge</hi> againſt theſe Delinquents, and <hi>the very form</hi> in which it was preferred: therefore I ſhall deſire him to <hi>view</hi> it throughly, whether there be <hi>that malignity</hi> in it which <hi>Byam</hi> declaims againſt? or whether he can in all theſe Depoſitions finde any thing to ground <hi>that aſsertion</hi> upon <hi>(Sect. 6.) that we were reſolved to unhinge the frame of authority; upon no other ſcore than to bring all things into diſorder, and out of the troubles patch up our decaying fortunes?</hi> or whether he can finde <hi>that confeſſion of theirs</hi> (Sect. 12.) <hi>that in taking this Shallop, they deſigned to arm and congregate themſelves against his Majeſties power?</hi> or any of <hi>thoſe plots</hi> (Sect. 13.) <hi>to r'ally all poſſible force to guard the river, to keep boats from the meeting, to ſeiz</hi> Byams <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall readily confeſſe that after a particular peruſal I can finde <hi>nothing like all or any of this, nor any other guilt than ſome innocent arts to recover their liberty, and ſome vehement expreſſions of their diſcontent to be deprived of their priviledges, and ſubjected under an arbitrary uſurp't
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105536:23"/>dominion;</hi> (for <hi>Right</hi> theſe rulers had none from <hi>the conſtitution of the Colony,</hi> and <hi>his Majeſties Authority, or any other,</hi> did not appear in it at all.) But, leſt <hi>interest</hi> cloud my eye, I will leave it to the <hi>Readers clearer judgement.</hi> However upon theſe Depoſitions <hi>theſe following ſentences</hi> were framed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Governour and General Aſſembly.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is ordered that Captain</hi> George Straunge, <hi>Capt.</hi> Thomas Crooke Mr. Tho. Archer, Mr. Peter Fabian <hi>be ſent off in the first ſhip bound either for</hi> England <hi>or the</hi> Barbados; <hi>and not to return for five years without</hi> his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties licence: <hi>and in the mean time to be ſecured</hi> under a ſtrong guard in irons, <hi>it having been proved by ſufficient evidence</hi> vivâ voce <hi>that they were</hi> moſt ſeditious, rebellious, <hi>and</hi> dangerous perſons.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dated</hi> 
                           <date> the 30<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                              <hi>of</hi> Nov. 1661.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed>W.B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Governour and General Aſſembly.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is ordered by the Authority aforeſaid that</hi> Mr. William Needham <hi>pay to the publick, one thouſand pounds of Sugar; and to be ſecured</hi> in irons under a ſtrong guard <hi>till he doth depart</hi> this Colony, <hi>which ſhall be in the firſt ſhip that ſhall ſet ſaile hence: it having been made evident that the ſaid</hi> Needham <hi>hath abetted and aſſiſted</hi> men in rebellion <hi>against the</hi> authority of the place <hi>and is a perſon most dangerous to</hi> this Colony.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Dated</hi> 
                           <date> the 30<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                              <hi>of</hi> Novemb 1661.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed>Will. Byam.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And leaſt the <hi>Reader</hi> ſhould have forgotten Mr. <hi>Needhams</hi> fact, it was, <hi>coming aboard the Prize with a launce and a piſtol;</hi> but when he ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently excuſed <hi>that,</hi> that <hi>Byam</hi> thought fit to diſcharge him; <hi>Marten</hi> told him it muſt not be, for he was <hi>a dangerous deſperate perſon, and had threatned him,</hi> and therefore <hi>he thought himſelf inſecure while the other remained in the Colony:</hi> Theſe weighty reaſons drew on <hi>this ſentence.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>Marten</hi> had been unhandſomely liberal of his tongue both againſt <hi>this Gentleman and his Wife,</hi> (a faculty which his diſeſteem of every one, <hi>that admires not him,</hi> prompts him to exerciſe) And <hi>Needham</hi> was too chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick to intend him a <hi>Baſtonado</hi> with ſilence, but muſt threaten it before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, and now is <hi>thus</hi> prevented.</p>
               <p>Accordingly were theſe unfortunate Gentlemen ſhackel'd like felons and expoſed to the deriſion of the ill-diſcerning rabble; kept about a fortnight under a numerous guard commanded by <hi>Uſher,</hi> and abuſed to the <hi>infaming</hi> of the <hi>gentility,</hi> if not <hi>humanity, of thoſe who countenanced,</hi> or rather <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined their ſufferings:</hi> and then at laſt with an armed force were thruſt aboard a rotten, leaky, broken-back't veſſel, with wives and children, their enemies being deaf to <hi>their protests,</hi> nay, beſpattering <hi>thoſe protests with the defames of a revived mutiny.</hi> They had not been three dayes at ſea when, the veſſel being ready to ſink under them, they were glad to run
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105536:24"/>her on the neareſt ſhore, which proved an adjacent Colony of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> in whoſe Port ſhe lodged unfit for a further voyage. Hence Mr. <hi>Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> as leaſt criminal, adventured up to <hi>Surinam</hi> in an <hi>Indian boat</hi> to crave leave of <hi>return</hi> for the reſt, at leaſt on <hi>Bail,</hi> till they could ſhip themſelves for ſome <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>their nation;</hi> or, if <hi>that</hi> would not be granted, permiſſion to remain in ſome nearer river where they might have greater hopes for tranſport, but could prevail in <hi>neither.</hi> Nay <hi>Byam and His</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored with the <hi>Dutch for their proſcription thence alſo; who,</hi> abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the virulence of his malice, <hi>increaſed their civility:</hi> thus they labour to reduce <hi>theſe innocents</hi> to an impoſſibility <hi>of publiſhing their ſufferings,</hi> and would have been beholding to any <hi>chance</hi> that would dip it ſelf <hi>in their bloud,</hi> and yet <hi>take the hazard and the puniſhment</hi> from them; leſs ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to juſtifie their actions <hi>before God then man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot but here, by the way, admire the conſtancy of ſome mens fate; among theſe gentlemen were divers who, for ſtanding in defence of the <hi>Royal Prerogative,</hi> of the <hi>peoples just priviledges,</hi> and in reſiſtance to an <hi>uſurp't dominion</hi> uſher'd in by a <hi>ſubverſion of legal rights,</hi> had, after many hazards and ſufferings, by baniſhment from their native <hi>England</hi> as traitours and rebels been expoſed to all the infortunes of needy wanderers; and theſe are now, for the ſame vertues, re-baniſhed with the ſame brands upon them; and put to <hi>repeat,</hi> or rather to <hi>perpetuate</hi> their never-paſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="deposition">
               <head>Depoſition.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> John Venman <hi>aged twenty eight years or thereabouts,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>The Deponent maketh oath that on the</hi> 26<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                  <hi>of this inſtant moneth of</hi> November, <hi>being commanded by Major</hi> Uſher <hi>and Captain</hi> Auguſtine Story <hi>to ſecure Captain</hi> Crook, <hi>Capt.</hi> George Straunge <hi>and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers committed priſoners at the houſe of</hi> Senior Henrico de Caſſeres <hi>where</hi> Mr. Stephen Neal <hi>liveth. Lieut. Col.</hi> Robert Sanford <hi>came aſhore and went into the priſoners, and after ſome diſcourſe paſſed, he came forth again and ſaid, Gentlemen I command you to lay down your armes; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, bade the priſoners come forth, and ſaid, follow me I will aſſiſt you with my life and fortunes: the Deponent made anſwer, that</hi> they <hi>(meaning the guards) were commanded there by a greater power then he was, and we will not lay down our armes till further order from our Governour: to which Lieut. Col.</hi> Sanford <hi>made anſwer that he was commanded by the</hi> Governour <hi>as well as Captain</hi> Story, <hi>and that he was</hi> his ſuperiour Officer, <hi>and that it was not lawfull to bear armes in time of peace. And further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne before me <dateline>
                     <date>the 29<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of Novemb. 1661.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W.B.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105536:24"/>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="deposition">
               <head type="sub">Mr. James Maxwel <hi>aged thirty years or thereabouts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>maketh oath, that at the ſame time aforeſaid he heard Lieutenant Col.</hi> Sanford <hi>command the priſoners to follow him, and commanded Capt.</hi> Story <hi>to lay down his armes; and further ſaith not.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne before me Die praedicto <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="deposition">
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>The Depoſition of</hi> Lieutenant William Burden <hi>aged twenty eight years or thereabouts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>The Deponent maketh oath, that on tueſday morning last (being the</hi> 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Novemb.) <hi>Lieut. Col.</hi> Sanford <hi>came out of the door where the priſoners were and ſaid, you that have any courage follow me and I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist you with my life and fortunes; whereupon they all followed him: Capt.</hi> Story <hi>cryed out, Gentlemen to your armes, and ſaid; Lieut. Col.</hi> Sanford <hi>be patient, and go over to the Governour, or otherwiſe I will ſend for him; he being on the other ſide of the river: this was at the houſe of</hi> Senior Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico de Caſſeres, <hi>where</hi> Mr. Stephen Neal <hi>now liveth.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Sworne before me <dateline>
                     <date>the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15, 16, 17" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>15, 16, 17. That particular in theſe Depoſitions, viz. <hi>of aſſiſting them with life and fortunes</hi> (which I onely controvert) I ſuppoſe was grounded on an <hi>ill underſtanding</hi> or <hi>hearing</hi> of my diſcourſe with Captain <hi>Story,</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> I ſaid, that <hi>if he would grant the cuſtody of the Priſoners to me I would engage my reputation, faith, life and fortunes for their forth-coming to a legal tryal:</hi> but be it as it may; the great crime inferr'd from hence is, that I being <hi>Lieutenant Collonel</hi> ſhould countermand the Order of my <hi>Collonel</hi> &amp;c. which ſome there, acquainted with little elſe but <hi>military punctilios,</hi> accounted ſo high a preſumption (if not worſe) that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it could not merit leſſe then a <hi>capital cenſure</hi> pronounced from a <hi>Martial Judicature.</hi> But (beſides that I think it ſafe for all in Authority well to ſtudy the <hi>Exceptions</hi> from that <hi>general rule</hi> in the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> before they too haſtily Erect <hi>military tribunals;</hi> leſt, e're they be aware, they <hi>ſubvert a fundamental law</hi>) I ſhall deſire <hi>thoſe raſh ſentencers</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that a <hi>regulated Militia may be in a place where the inhabitants are not in a poſture of warre nor under the Dominion of any, but the civil ſword:</hi> and that <hi>in ſuch a place, it is no intrenchment on the lawes of war, nor tryable in martial courts, if the inferiour Officer contest, though to actual violences, with his ſuperiour:</hi> and ſuch is the ſtate of the preſent queſtion; onely what makes it more ſtrong on my part, <hi>his Commiſſion</hi> for <hi>Collonel</hi> was actually determined by the expreſs limitation of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from whence he firſt and onely derived it; whereas it is controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, <hi>whether I being, indefinitely, without ſuch limitation, appointed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105536:25"/>Lieutenant Collonel of the Regiment and Judge of the Court of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas, by the Election and Act of the General Aſſembly</hi> (who could only appoint all inferiour Miniſters) <hi>did not continue ſuch, till the Act by which I was empowred were repealed.</hi> Nor would I <hi>from this aſſert,</hi> that <hi>I was more rightly in power then Byam</hi> (for God is my witneſs that very willingly I would have ſhaken <hi>the burthen of publick adminiſtrations</hi> off my ſhoulders; and the ſenſible part of that Colony know <hi>how induſtriouſly I have declined all thoſe Employments:</hi> ſo farre was I from that <hi>ridiculous ambition</hi> of making my ſelf Governour; to be <hi>diſproved</hi> by <hi>many inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, proved</hi> by <hi>none.</hi>) Let <hi>this truth</hi> onely take place, <hi>that neither of us had a just power,</hi> and then that objection againſt me hath loſt its ſting.</p>
               <p>Yet, had their Authority been as legal as they could have deſired it to be, my fact is but onely <hi>an attempt of reſcous</hi> which was not <hi>effected;</hi> nor was any greater violence <hi>then of words,</hi> formed into <hi>perſwaſions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> employed on <hi>that attempt; no evill conſequences</hi> followed it; the priſoners <hi>ſtill remained in the cuſtody of the guards,</hi> and <hi>thoſe guards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violated:</hi> certainly, if a ſimple reſcous, though ſucceeded in, be not a crime for which a man muſt looſe <hi>fame, liberty, eſtate and countrey,</hi> I am hardly dealt with, that have loſt <hi>all theſe,</hi> and my <hi>ruine entailed on my children,</hi> for poorly <hi>attempting a Reſcous with arguments onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to make my fault <hi>yet leſs, they had no lawfull power; and acted by an illegal force to the deſtruction of the birth-right of their fellow ſubjects; which by this action of mine</hi> I endeavoured to <hi>prevent,</hi> and, had it ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>had certainly prevented it,</hi> and <hi>made up all theſe breaches; which</hi> was the <hi>onely end</hi> in my eye. And they that will <hi>from this onely fact,</hi> conclude that <hi>I excited to the cauſalities of theſe mens impriſonment,</hi> and bring <hi>no other inſtance</hi> for their <hi>ſo concluding,</hi> may as rationally affirm, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a man endeavours to worke the eſcape of his friend,</hi> therefore <hi>he acted with him in what drew on his reſtraint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have already particularized in my tryal, where the onely ſentence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to my ear was <hi>to be laid in the hold in irons,</hi> which was preſently executed; but about ten dayes after the <hi>Secretary</hi> brought me <hi>their whole condemnation</hi> (<hi>dated,</hi> and I believe <hi>decreed, before my day of hearing</hi>) in theſe words.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>By the Governour and General Aſſembly.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It is ordered by the Authority aforeſaid, that Lieut. Col.</hi> Robert San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford <hi>pay unto the Publick five thouſand pounds of Sugar, and to be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloſe priſoner in irons till a ſhip ſail hence for</hi> England, <hi>it being made appear before</hi> this Authority <hi>by ſeveral evidences that the ſaid Lieut. Col.</hi> Robert Sanford <hi>in a most rebellious and mutinous manner, came to the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105536:25"/>houſe where ſeveral perſons who had taken up armes against the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Colony and had acted feloniouſly, were committed, and would contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all law and order, not onely have diſcharged them, but commanded them out of the ſaid houſe, and heading them proffered to aſſiſt them with his life and fortunes: and being called before</hi> this Authority, <hi>then ſitting on the Examination and Judging of theſe</hi> ſeditious <hi>and</hi> rebellious <hi>perſons,</hi> denyed <hi>and</hi> abuſed the ſaid Authority.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Dated <date>the 28<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
                              <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1661.</date>
                        </dateline> 
                        <signed>W. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>At the inſtant of my receiving <hi>this</hi> I paid down my fine and took the Treaſurers diſcharge, hoping that I might have prevailed to have been ſent off to <hi>Barbados</hi> with the other Gentlemen, and ſo have been the ſooner freed from my hateful reſtraint, and <hi>their power</hi> alſo among whom I thought my life not over-ſecure.</p>
               <p>And were I as earneſt <hi>to make my enemies odious</hi> as they are <hi>to befilth us with any ſort of dirt,</hi> I could bring fair evidences of a <hi>Practice</hi> againſt me <hi>whoſe barbariſme</hi> exceeds <hi>any</hi> yet inſtanced in. But though it concernes <hi>them,</hi> in the part they have to act, to make us at leaſt <hi>ſeem criminal;</hi> (to doe which they therefore gladly recurre to every, though improbable, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny) to <hi>me</hi> it is ſufficient that <hi>I appear innocent:</hi> wherefore I ſhall not lengthen my diſcourſe with any digreſſion not abſolutely pertinent <hi>to my juſtification, though it conduce largely to their blackning; That,</hi> if I appear faultleſs, being <hi>fully enough effected</hi> by <hi>ſuch uſage</hi> of me <hi>as themſelves do own.</hi> I hartily forgive <hi>the intention</hi> who ever was guilty of it, and deſire <hi>God may do ſo too:</hi> 'tis enough for me that <hi>I am ſafe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Often did I labour by letters to <hi>Byam</hi> to purchaſe the favour of as ſpeedy a baniſhment as my Compeers were like to enjoy, and as often had my ſuit rejected; <hi>The Councel</hi> was courted, but with <hi>like ſucceſs; the General Aſſembly,</hi> forſooth, <hi>had determined my puniſhment and they onely could retract the Order.</hi> To <hi>them</hi> I therefore applyed my ſelf for permiſſion to goe to <hi>Barbados:</hi> my importunity at length prevailed, and on the 25<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> day of <hi>January,</hi> in the <hi>cloſe of the day,</hi> I was put aboard a ſhip bound for <hi>that Iſland:</hi> the firſt minute of liberty I enjoyed ſince the 26<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> day of <hi>Novemb.</hi> in the morning; two or three dayes of which I was ſhut up in the ſtinking hold of the ſhallop, &amp; all the reſt of the time laden with <hi>villeinous ſhackles:</hi> but by this detention I eſcaped thoſe <hi>calamities</hi> which my brethren in exile were, by reaſon of the <hi>crazineſs of their veſſel,</hi> expoſed unto; and arrived ſafely at <hi>Barbados</hi> and from <hi>thence</hi> hither to <hi>England</hi> before any news could informe me that <hi>they</hi> were yet among the living. And thus after an expence of nine years pretious time, in all which with an unaltered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy I laboured in <hi>that Colonies promotion,</hi> and, to the frequent hazard
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105536:26"/>of my perſon and detriment to my eſtate, acted more <hi>in the publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes</hi> then any one Gentleman beſides, and <hi>with leſs conſideration for my ſelf;</hi> now, when I juſt began to taſte the fruits of my ſo long toil, I am thruſt from <hi>thence</hi> and <hi>them</hi> with a violent Impulſion, for no other cauſe but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-tendering the lives of my <hi>dearest friend</hi> and <hi>nearest relation;</hi> which, rationally enough, I imagined <hi>on the precipice of danger.</hi> I conſidered a taken life like ſplit water was never to be gathered up again; &amp; knowing that there was both <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> in making <hi>their reſcous,</hi> the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of preſerving lives ſo dear, wing'd me for <hi>the attempt,</hi> and tangled me in the <hi>toyles</hi> of my <hi>deadly-hating enemies.</hi> I, who glory in nothing ſo much as <hi>an untainted loyalty,</hi> whoſe <hi>moſt certain religion is obedience to the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Power,</hi> who onely <hi>out of veneration to the name of his ſacred Majeſty</hi> had ſubjected my ſelf <hi>to leſs then the ſhadow of his Proclamation, to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then the aire of his commands, a Nothing which had uſurp't his name;</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> I was hitherto complyant in all things, and had <hi>ſtill ſo been</hi> had not <hi>ſuch lives, ſo illegally,</hi> been threatned; <hi>must fall now</hi> with thoſe abominated imputations of <hi>faction, ſedition, treaſon,</hi> and <hi>rebellion; ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrent from my ſoul,</hi> caſt on me to hurry me <hi>into the deepeſt abyſs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy: and all this</hi> for endeavouring <hi>to fly the perſecution of an uſurping Tyrant.</hi> But my great conſolation is, <hi>the ſame</hi> imputation, by <hi>the ſame</hi> ſort of men, caſt on thouſands that acted <hi>the ſame</hi> things, have, for many luſtres of years, been <hi>the onely crown for the moſt prodigious loyalty:</hi> and 'tis poſſible <hi>the ſame</hi> planet ſtill retains ſome vigour of its <hi>Malignancy,</hi> eſpecially at ſo great a diſtance <hi>from the Royal beams.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, indeed (if it be not criminal to confeſs ſo much) I was not leſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>with the conſideration of the danger our most ſacred laws were in</hi> (to which I was ſworne a Magiſtrate acting by vertue of a Power derived from the Delegates <hi>ſubordinate to our ſoveraign lord the King</hi>) then I was with <hi>natural inclinations</hi> to my <hi>periſhing intimates.</hi> Having alwaies been <hi>loyal</hi> (or a <hi>traitour</hi> if I may ſo ſpeak <hi>in the Dialect of thoſe times</hi>) when thoſe <hi>Infamous rebels</hi> of our laſt age, <hi>without</hi> and <hi>against the King,</hi> made <hi>the ruine of our fundamental ſanctions, the ground-work of their uſurp't dominion;</hi> I durſt not become <hi>diſloyal,</hi> or <hi>really a traitour, now,</hi> when <hi>thoſe ſame lawes</hi> were trampled on to <hi>the ſame end,</hi> by abetting <hi>theſe uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers;</hi> ſo much <hi>the more infamous for pretending</hi> (to His greater indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) <hi>to act by the Kings Authority.</hi> And therefore I rather choſe by a <hi>ſingle oppoſition</hi> to fall in defence of our <hi>Soveraigns honour and laws,</hi> then to <hi>troop with them</hi> from <hi>whom</hi> I alwaies had a <hi>natural averſation.</hi> And I count it ſomething of glory, that ſince <hi>in the times of need</hi> I lay under the imperfections of <hi>non-age</hi> and <hi>abſence,</hi> and could not <hi>therefore,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105536:26"/>act my affections to the Royal cauſe,</hi> I am yet, in the laſt hour of the day, thought worthy of <hi>thoſe titles, which</hi> (though in themſelves the higheſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals) are yet by glorious accidents become <hi>the most honourable additions to his Majeſties most conſtant ſervants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have onely to ſpeak to the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of <hi>Byams Declaration,</hi> and ſo ſhall take leave of my <hi>Reader.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Objections made by the Delinquents.</head>
               <p>Sect. 1. <hi>That the Governour was</hi> Elective <hi>by the Countrey, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but one year, according to the eſtabliſhed conſtitution of the Colony; and therefore his continuance therein for any longer time without the choice and annual Election of the</hi> Delegates <hi>of the ſeveral Diviſions of the Colony is an</hi> uſurpation <hi>upon the liberties of the people.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1 He neither inſerts our objections <hi>truly</hi> nor <hi>fully;</hi> for we objected that the Conſtitution of the Delegates was, <hi>that yearly the people ſhould by their Election renew the whole Authority, both Governour, Councel, and Aſſembly:</hi> and that the <hi>Delegates</hi> did <hi>ſo decree</hi> we prove from <hi>Byams last Commiſſion,</hi> dated the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>: <hi>of June</hi> 1660. by the onely vertue of which both <hi>he</hi> and <hi>this whole General Aſſembly got poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Government;</hi> in <hi>which Commiſſion their decree</hi> is expreſſed in theſe plain engliſh words. <hi>That the free-holders of each Diviſion doe, annually, upon the first wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in</hi> June, <hi>meet; and, by their free voices, elect three able, honeſt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet men, free-holders and inhabitants in their reſpective Diviſions, to be their Repreſentatives for the following year, that theſe</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Diviſions were in numb. ſeaven.</note> 
                  <hi>twenty one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives be the General Aſſembly, in whom is the ſupream Power and Government of this Countrey both Legiſlative and Magiſtratical</hi> (with ſubordination and ſubjection to the ſoveraignty and lawes of England, as in the Preamble) <hi>and that They meet the ſecond wedneſday in</hi> June <hi>at the publick place at Toorárica, and there appoint from amongst themſelves a Governour for that year</hi> &amp;c. So that by <hi>this Act,</hi> the former cuſtome, which he hinteth at, viz. <hi>[of the peoples first chooſing the Delegates, then the Delegates chooſing the Governour, the Governour his Councel, and, after that, the people to meet again to elect their Aſſembly men]</hi> was diſcontinued; and <hi>this other forme</hi> ordained to all futurity till determined by the commands of our ſoveraign. And though <hi>Byam</hi> pretended to <hi>thoſe commands,</hi> yet he may remember (for he accuſeth us of it, <hi>Sect.</hi> 8.) that the foundation on which we firmed our objection was, <hi>that his Majeſty had not yet determined this conſtitution by his Royal commands. That very Governour,</hi> indeed, and <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> to whom
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105536:27"/>the Government was committed by <hi>theſe ſame Delegates</hi> (at the inſtant when they made <hi>this Eſtabliſhment</hi>) for <hi>that year and no longer,</hi> ſo abuſed the <hi>trust repoſed in them</hi> that in their very firſt year they paſſed an <hi>Order for their own perpetuation;</hi> to which when we objected, <hi>that they, being an inferiour power to that of the Delegates from whom they had their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, could not annull their ſanctions;</hi> they confuted us by <hi>armes, irons, fines, and baniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>Anſwer to the Delinquents objections.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. It is granted that the Governour was elected by the Countrey, &amp; by the eſtabliſhed conſtitution of the Colony he was to be elected an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually at a day certain by the Delegates of the ſeveral diviſions of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and by vertue thereof was to continue therein but one year.</p>
               <p>But as to <hi>this eſtabliſhment</hi> it is to be conſidered <hi>wherefore</hi> &amp; <hi>when</hi> it was made, it was in the juncture of time when the whole frame of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in confuſion and out of order; the legal authority rejected by a violent power, who had aſſumed to themſelves the ſupream power of our Nation; and <hi>that</hi> at the firſt eſtabliſhment was <hi>elective,</hi> in ſemblance to <hi>which this</hi> was made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. He ſhould grant, as I ſaid before, that <hi>the repreſentatives,</hi> in whom was <hi>the Government,</hi> were to be yearly elected, and that <hi>they</hi> from amongſt <hi>themſelves</hi> were to name a <hi>Governour at a day certain</hi> (who was no other but their <hi>preſident or ſpeaker;</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> at the meetings, <hi>ſtiled</hi>) And <hi>this eſtabliſhment</hi> was made in <hi>June</hi> 1660. when the <hi>King</hi> was happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the <hi>dominion</hi> of his <hi>people.</hi> And though indeed we then had no <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his return,</hi> yet we knew how far the ever-famous <hi>D. of Albemarle</hi> had acted in order to it; and <hi>that the Free-Parliament was actually ſitting:</hi> nor was <hi>this establiſhment</hi> made in ſemblance <hi>to any form of government</hi> ſet up <hi>here at home</hi> in the times of the <hi>late uſurpation;</hi> not any in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony (except the <hi>authour of this concluſion,</hi> if I gueſs right by the <hi>ſtile</hi>) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt <hi>eſteem</hi> of thoſe <hi>deſtructive innovations;</hi> but rather in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>that conſtitution in Barbadoes,</hi> which is ruled by a <hi>Governour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned from the Soveraign, a Councel of his own chuſing, and an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> (two out of every pariſh) <hi>yearly elected by the people,</hi> which whole body is called the <hi>Governour and General Aſſembly.</hi> Now we wanting <hi>a Commiſſion from the King,</hi> were forced to content our ſelves for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> onely, <hi>choſen by the people,</hi> who for <hi>order</hi> ſake (as thoſe in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> do) made <hi>one</hi> of themſelves the <hi>Speaker,</hi> and, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to attract the peoples reverence, gave him <hi>the title of Governour.</hi> And becauſe upon every emergency to convent <hi>this whole body,</hi> was thought a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105536:27"/>trouble and inconveniency, therefore they permitted the <hi>Governour</hi> to name ſix of theſe <hi>repreſentatives</hi> (one out of <hi>each diviſion</hi> his own excepted) to be his <hi>Councel</hi> and adviſe with him in the regulating the Colony according to the <hi>Laws of England,</hi> and the <hi>By-laws of this General Aſſembly.</hi> Now upon the whole matter the queſtions are, <hi>whether the inhabitants of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony of</hi> Surinam <hi>being left without conduct, might not agree amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on ſome form of rule to which they would ſubmit till concluded by their Soveraign: &amp;, whether thoſe that were put into authority by ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact were not bound thereby?</hi> If it be anſwered <hi>negatively,</hi> then <hi>Byam and the reſt</hi> had never any <hi>rightfull authority;</hi> if <hi>affirmatively,</hi> then their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority expired in <hi>June</hi> 62. and in either caſe whatever was ſaid or done againſt them <hi>at this time,</hi> could neither be ſedition nor oppoſition; nay, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asmuch as it appears that they made <hi>the firſt aſſault, by impriſoning</hi> Jones, <hi>and endeavouring the like to others,</hi> whatever <hi>thoſe perſons, ſo aſſaulted and proſecuted,</hi> did act, attempt, or intend was onely <hi>to defend themſelves</hi> from their unruly neighbours. And ſo much doth our <hi>natural ligeance</hi> to our <hi>Soveraign</hi> (of which neither <hi>time nor place</hi> can diſcharge us) entitle us to the <hi>Royal Protection,</hi> and the being <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> to the <hi>priviledges of our Charter;</hi> that I cannot think a <hi>company of us</hi> can in any part of the world be <hi>ſo left to our ſelves,</hi> as that <hi>the greater number may impunely invade the rights of the leſs, and deſtroy them in perſon, honour, liberty, and eſtate:</hi> Eſpecially when we had agreed amongſt our ſelves (and <hi>ſealed that agreement by proclaiming his Majeſty, and ſwearing allegiance to him</hi>) <hi>to retain our King, our allegeance, and our laws.</hi> Nor can it be rationally affirmed that our <hi>proclaiming the King altered our conſtitution,</hi> unleſs we had unitely agreed <hi>that it ſhould do ſo;</hi> for we had in <hi>general terms before ſubjected our ſelves and conſtitution to the Soveraign power of our Nation,</hi> and that <hi>after proclaiming of his Sacred Majeſty</hi> was onely an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that <hi>ſuch a particular perſon was our Sovereign;</hi> which could not void our contract, ſince one article of it was <hi>that nothing ſhould void it but the Kings commands.</hi> And that we did not think the <hi>Kings</hi> coming in, or <hi>our proclaiming him,</hi> and <hi>annulling of our government,</hi> is evident from the <hi>Commiſſions</hi> which <hi>Byam (by order of the General Aſſembly)</hi> granted ſometime after this; whereof I have two, whoſe ſtile is, <hi>By vertue of a power unto us from the delegates ſubordinate to our Soveraign Lord, Charles, &amp;c.</hi> Nor do I finde (though it ſhould invalidate the <hi>Delegates decree</hi>) how his <hi>Majeſties reſtauration doth inveſt Byam,</hi> or any other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon, <hi>with the Government.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>Sect. 3. <hi>As to the reaſons why it was made, they were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe; in that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105536:28"/>we were many of his Majeſties liedge people who had embarqued our ſelves and fortunes in order to the planting and ſettling of</hi> this Colony; <hi>as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour over whom by the then ſupream power of</hi> England <hi>Colonel</hi> Richard Holdip <hi>was</hi> commiſſioned <hi>and</hi> ſent: his <hi>declining of which, and thereby leaving the place</hi> deſtitute of any ſuch authorized government; and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power of <hi>England, (by reaſon of their many diſtractions and revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Government)</hi> taking no further cognizance of us; <hi>we, the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this place, being</hi> neceſſitated <hi>thereunto, in order to the civil and peaceable Government and preſervation of every one in his life, and liberty, and eſtate in this Colony (as the records hereof do manifeſt) made</hi> this eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment <hi>for our Government,</hi> it to continue with ſubmiſſion to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority of England. <hi>Now</hi> thus, <hi>and according to</hi> this eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>did the Governour that now is become Governour in poſseſſion; of</hi> which <hi>(his Majeſty being mercifully reſtored to the regal and happy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Nation)</hi> his Declaration for the continuation of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, Magiſtrates, and Officers to continue in their ſeveral powers, and authorities, till his Royal pleaſure were further known and ſignified, found him, and hath and doth empower, authorize, and continue him therein till his further order. <hi>So that now he ſtands no longer Governour by vertue of the eſtabliſhment of the Colony, but is authorized, empowred, and confirmed therein by his Majeſties Declaration, which is the ſupream authority of our Nation:</hi> In ſubmiſſion to which this eſtabliſhment <hi>(as it ought, ſo it)</hi> was made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Governour thus authorized, empowred, and confirmed Governour by the</hi> Kings Declaration, <hi>doth, as a relative and neceſſary incident and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent thereunto, ſtand accountable to the</hi> King <hi>for the Government of</hi> this place, <hi>and cannot without the forfeiture of his faith and allegiance to his ſacred Majeſty either render up, or paſſively ſuffer his power as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be taken from him; eſpecially we having owned his Majeſty as our ſupream Magiſtrate by our ſolemn proclaiming of him, and recognized up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our publick records, our Governour as his Governour, virtually by his Majeſties Declaration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Governour thus authorized, empowred, and confirmed by the Kings Declaration; and his power and authority therein as Governour by virtue thereof recognized by us upon our own Records, the diſowning of him ſo to be, and the declaring and endeavouring by an Overt act to ſet up and exect any other Governour, in oppoſition to, and contempt of, the</hi> King <hi>his</hi> Crown <hi>and</hi> Dignity, <hi>ſignified by his</hi> Royal Will <hi>and</hi> Pleaſure, <hi>requiring our ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and obedience to his commands and Declaration,</hi> is treaſon in ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers and contrivers.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105536:28"/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. At length out comes the true reaſon for <hi>this eſtabliſhment,</hi> but it is not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. 1. That <hi>Byam</hi> plaid <hi>the ſeditions perſon</hi> (when out of all publick emploiment) <hi>and raiſed many diſputes againſt the power left in poſſeſsion of the Government by Holdip</hi> (and therein continued by the peoples repreſentatives) <hi>as not ſufficiently authorized, inſtigating the people to an actual diſobedience.</hi> Nor, 2. That, <hi>though at that time I had the ſword of that authority in my hand, and the authority to back me, yet I did not drive him into exile, but made way for him to the Chair, by perſwading thoſe that ſate in it to deſcend, and give the people leave to place in it whom they liked beſt.</hi> Nor, 3. That after all this <hi>(notwithſtanding the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes he had particularly againſt me in all his m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vings to ſedition, in emulation of my eminency, and diſdain of his own nullity) I laid on many on that heap of votes which mounted him to his height; therein conſulting the Colonies, not my own, advance; this perſon being of ſo reſtleſſe an Ambition, that if he ruled not all there was no ruling him.</hi> But of <hi>this</hi> no more.</p>
               <p>He <hi>thus</hi> coming to <hi>the poſſeſsion</hi> of the Government, labours every year to be perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated <hi>without an annual ſtanding candidate;</hi> and at laſt fearing to hazard himſelf longer on the unconſtant multitude (<hi>elated</hi> alſo with <hi>the conſcience of his ſufferings and ſervice in the Royal cauſe</hi>) ſaies, <hi>I will continue,</hi> and <hi>I will ſay the King hath ſo commanded;</hi> and <hi>I will with force drive away all thoſe that have hitherto, and ſtill ſhall, impede me herein, be their conſtant loyalty never ſo exemplar.</hi> For what is all this talk of the <hi>Kings proclamation</hi> but <hi>Byams ipſe dixit?</hi> Nay, what is it elſe but <hi>a meer fiction,</hi> raiſed from a <hi>preſumption</hi> that (probably enough) <hi>the King in this ſo great a change might ſo proclaim?</hi> And <hi>theſe ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Arguments</hi> (or more truly<note n="*" place="margin">Major <hi>Noel</hi> the ſcribler of this Concluſion; a worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of <hi>O. Cromwel,</hi> and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher (in his motto) over the martyred <hi>Charles</hi> with <hi>devict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hoſte libertate donati.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Noellian Inganneations</hi>) drawn from <hi>this ſuppoſal,</hi> are but like <hi>thoſe</hi> about the <hi>Golden tooth,</hi> which proved at laſt <hi>a forgery.</hi> But though <hi>to expend wit on an erroneous principle may conſiſt with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</hi> yet to joyn with thoſe <hi>whom onely forgetfulneſs hath left out of the liſt of traytours and rebels</hi> in beſpotting a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, never-varied loyalty,</hi> with the abominated aſperſions of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> pulling <hi>Ruine</hi> on whole families, and <hi>all by a miſtake</hi> (ſhould I exclude <hi>malice</hi>) cannot but by <hi>juſtice</hi> be condemned <hi>as a criminal temerity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I need not controvert the <hi>Law</hi> our <hi>Surinam Iudge</hi> ſo <hi>Magiſterially</hi> concludes with; but ſhall onely add theſe few aſſertions out of <hi>Iudge Ienkins,</hi> fol. 195. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To alter the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Lawes in any part by <hi>force</hi> is <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> To uſurp the Royal Power is <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> To ſubvert the Fundamental lawes is <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> A neceſſity of a mans own making doth not excuſe him. Preſentment, or tryal by Iury is the <hi>Birth right</hi> of the ſubject. <hi>Magna charta,</hi> the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and other good laws of this land ordain, that all mens tryals ſhould be by the eſtabliſhed laws and not otherwiſe, they are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of the <hi>Petition of Right.</hi> An Act of Parliament that a man ſhould be judge in his own cauſe is a void Act. <hi>ib. fol.</hi> 139. The common law of this land is, that every Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ſubject to a tryal by <hi>Bill of Attainder</hi> in Parliament, wherein the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>both Houſes</hi> muſt neceſſarily concur, for <hi>that tryal</hi> is <hi>an Act of Parliament</hi> to which all men are ſubject: But otherwiſe no man ſhall be deſtroyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but by the lawfull judgement of his <hi>Peers,</hi> or by the <hi>Common law</hi> of the land. <hi>ib. fol.</hi> 93.</p>
               <p>The Governour and General Aſſembly (as they call themſelves) of <hi>Surinam</hi> do here confeſs that in our tryal and puniſhment they have uſurped a Power equal, if not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to <hi>that of the King and both houſes of Parliament, ſubverted the fundamental Laws, end by force of an Army altered the eſtabliſhed Lawes of England in the whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From my <hi>own reading</hi> I ſhall ſubjoine <hi>this,</hi> to diſcharge men guilty of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Felony,</hi> is <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Felony:</hi> Byam <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have accuſed us of <hi>both,</hi> puniſhed us for <hi>neither:</hi> if we be guilty, they are anſwerable for not bringing us to a tryal; if we be innocent, they are puilty of <hi>conſpiracy:</hi> nor can they avoid <hi>this Dilemma</hi> by objecting our Irons, Fines,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105536:29"/>and Baniſhment, for all lawyers know <hi>theſe</hi> are not the <hi>puniſhments</hi> for <hi>treaſon</hi> nor <hi>felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;</hi> nor had we <hi>the tryal</hi> due to <hi>either:</hi> they did <hi>this way</hi> indeed <hi>revenge themſelves</hi> on <hi>ſome</hi> for endeavouring to unfix them in their <hi>uſurp't dominion,</hi> and on <hi>me</hi> for labouring to diſappoint them of <hi>their revenge,</hi> which may, poſſibly, be termed an <hi>inconſiderate,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rationally be cenſured a <hi>criminal attempt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Copy of a Letter which <hi>Byam</hi> ſent to <hi>Barbados</hi> to my Uncle, together with <hi>this his Declaration.</hi> Superſcribed.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For Captain <hi>Nathaniel Kingsland</hi> my reſpected friend.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOur affection to, and intereſt in, this Colony are ſufficient obligations to render you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the late diſtempers in our Government: and I am ſorry to tell you that your Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew. Lieutenant Col.</hi> Robert Sanford, <hi>hath not onely</hi> abetted, <hi>but</hi> hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed <hi>the unruly au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours of our ſad diſturbance; I have encloſed preſented you with an</hi> impartial relation <hi>of all paſſages moſt remarkable, wherein I have not the leaſt been ſwayed by</hi> prejudice <hi>or</hi> animoſity. <hi>What fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e thus hurried him to that exceſs of inſolence I cannot well judge, unleſs ſoaring too high with an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ver weening gale of his natural and acquired parts, which too early advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to publick offices of Eminency in the Colony; he unadviſedly over-ſet for want of the</hi> ballaſt <hi>of</hi> experience <hi>and</hi> diſcretion: <hi>had be learn's to</hi> obey, <hi>before he</hi> commanded, <hi>he would not have</hi> commanded <hi>before he</hi> obeyed, <hi>which you finde was his</hi> errour: <hi>what</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy <hi>he may preſent you for it I know not, I am ſure I have not painted it ſo foul as it really was.</hi> Sir, <hi>when you have peruſed the incloſed papers be pleaſed to recommend them to the view of</hi> Mr. John Kirton <hi>and Sergeant Major</hi> Authony Rous, <hi>to whom I deſire my reſpects and ſervice may be preſented.</hi>— (then after a general accompt of the Colonies preſent condition he concludes) <hi>your Nephew had of late a deſire to give you a viſit, which I could not admit at preſent, being the poſitive order for his departure was for</hi> London <hi>which was his deſire; nor would I reverſe what the united authority had concluded on. If I may ſerve you in theſe parts you may he aſſured of my readineſs and fidelity. I wiſh you happineſs and reſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Surinam <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>of Decemb.</hi> 1661.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your very affectionate friend and ſervant</hi> William Byam.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This was writ and ſent away by thoſe other <hi>Proſcripes,</hi> while I remained behind in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but their veſſel failing them I came to and from the <hi>Barbados</hi> before this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived there, and ſo never ſaw it till I received it, <hi>ſent from my Vncle,</hi> here in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105536:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
